<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An awakening warning to the wofull world by a voyce in three nations uttered in a brief dissertation concerning that fatal and to be admired conjunction of all the planets in one and the same sign, Sagittarius ... to come to pass the 1/11 day of December, anno 1662 : in which it is clearly evinced, as well by S. Scriptures ... that the glorious coming of Jesus Christ is at hand ... / autore Petro Serario.</title>
            <author>Serrurier, Petrus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09029507</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09029507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59217)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1294:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An awakening warning to the wofull world by a voyce in three nations uttered in a brief dissertation concerning that fatal and to be admired conjunction of all the planets in one and the same sign, Sagittarius ... to come to pass the 1/11 day of December, anno 1662 : in which it is clearly evinced, as well by S. Scriptures ... that the glorious coming of Jesus Christ is at hand ... / autore Petro Serario.</title>
                  <author>Serrurier, Petrus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>42 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterodam [sic.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42297:1"/>
            <p>An AWAKENING WARNING TO THE VVofull VVorld, By a Voyce in three Nations; Uttered in a brief DISSERTATION Concerning that <hi>Fatal,</hi> and <hi>to be admired Conjunction</hi> of all the Planets, in one, and the ſame Sign ( ♐ ) <hi>Sagitarius, the last of the fiery T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>plicity,</hi> to come to paſs the 1/11 day of <hi>December,</hi> Anno 1662.</p>
            <p>IN WHICH It is clearly evinced, as well by S. Scriptures, as by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Conjunction it ſelf, and other Antecedents, Concomitants and Circumſtances, that the Glorious Coming of JESUS CHRIST is at hand.</p>
            <p>WHEREBY
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>He will recollect the Diſperſed Nation of the</hi> Jevvs.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Aboliſh the man of Sin, who hitherto hath obtained the Principality, as well in the Church as in the world.</hi> And</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>At length erect his Glorious Kingdom on Earth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Autore PETRO SERARIO.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dam,</hi> MDCLXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42297:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IF any trust to Heav'ns, or lights preſage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some truth; lift up your hearts thou preſent age.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If to beleeve what earth gives to the eye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or to the hand to feel, there's reaſon why;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beleeve O mortals this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> time declines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Starres to their Maker, their Pow'r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reſign.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O that to th' world, (ah which we too much truſt)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wee'ld ſay, pack hence give place to God all muſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lo this world rues, and ſo doth Babe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And whoſoever ſtands for Babel ſhall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He only ſhall eſcape deſtruction,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That's firmly joyn'd to Chriſt in union.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chooſe which thou'lſt rather have; the laſt hour runs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which past, no ſcap, nor choice to mortall ſons.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The day invades, wiſht for in ev'ry age</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When God alone ſhall Rule this earthly Stage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And with him Saints (to whom the promiſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To be the Heirs thereof ſhall come to paſs.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <head>The Sign of <hi>Sagitarius.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of planetary positions</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>The Situation of the Planets at Noon</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>day of</hi> December <hi>is thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to their <hi>Latitude,</hi> all decline from the Ecliptick, towards the North, only <hi>Mars</hi> is found in the Southern Climate.</p>
            <p>According to their <hi>Longitude,</hi> thus they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed, according to the Degrees and Minutes of <hi>Sagitarius.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>♃—0—9.♐</item>
                  <item>♀—4—59.♐</item>
                  <item>♄—9—25.♐</item>
                  <item>☿—10—55.♐</item>
                  <item>☉—19—46.♐</item>
                  <item>♂—25—44.♐</item>
                  <item>
                     <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>—27—54.♐</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42297:2"/>
            <head>Well-affected Reader,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here lately came forth at <hi>Groning,</hi> a little Book in heir Native Language, concerning this Matter, Entituled <hi>WAT NIEWS</hi> and <hi>WAT WONDELIKS,</hi> &amp;c. not only ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the true <hi>Hiſtory of this Conjunction,</hi> and the <hi>Deſcription of the Celeſtial Theatre,</hi> in which this Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acted, together with the <hi>Properties and Operations of the Planets,</hi> the Actors in this Scene, but alſo ſubjoyning <hi>a very ſerious and moſt pious Exhortation,</hi> by which the Author would have us admoniſhed, that we heed theſe things, and convert in Sackcloath and Aſhes, that we periſh not by the invading Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which of neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y come un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>voidably upon the earth; but that we may be graciouſly preſerved.</p>
            <p>After this Book by and by ſucceeded another in the <hi>German</hi> Tongue, brought out of <hi>Germany</hi> unto us, bearing the name of a FORERUNNER
<note n="*" place="margin">Orig. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omus.</note>, becauſe in it was this <hi>Concurſe of all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> in the ſame Sign, as ſome eminent, and notable <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſenger,</hi> and <hi>Significator</hi> of the things which ſhall follow that great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction which ſhall be in the Year 1663 next enſuing. Which <hi>Forerunner,</hi> indeed, doth excellently harmoniſe with the for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er Book; and doth alike ſeriouſly and piouſly moniſh, concerning many things; eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecially of the <hi>Times of the Gentiles now expiring;</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> of the <hi>Approach of the Converſion and Reſtitution of the Jews;</hi> and doubtleſs of the <hi>imminent end of this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe I perceived, that among other Obſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cles which bolt the door againſt theſe ſo ſaving monitions, and the truth therein contained, whereby they are leſs entertained by men of the preſent Generation, this is not the meaneſt, that there is ſuch <hi>ſmall Attention lent to the Celestial Signes,</hi> and ſo little
<note n="*" place="margin">Orig. Fides</note> Credit given, as if what things are in the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vens, are ſo above us, as if
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42297:3"/>they nothing appertained to us. Touching the <hi>Sun,</hi> indeed, all confeſs it procreates to us Day and Night, Summer and Winter, fruitfulneſs and barrenneſs: And as to the <hi>Moon,</hi> none will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that it exerciſeth ſome dominion on earth, not only on the flowing and reflowing of the Sea, but alſo on the Humors and Complexions of men: inſomuch that it cannot be denied much to be our concern, how theſe Lights are in Heaven placed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, whether conjunct or ſeparate, whether farther diſtant each from o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mutually near approiching; whether the Moon makes towards the Sun, or recedes from it. Moreover who knows not how much it concernes, in what place of Heaven, and in what Sign, and with what Aſſociates ſhe enters into the Bride-chamber of her <hi>Husband;</hi> and what Prognoſticks the skilful in Aſtrology are wont from hence to infer and predict. But as what apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o other Planets and Luminaries of Heaven, <hi>v.g.</hi>
               <note place="margin">♄ Saturn.</note>
               <note place="margin">♃ J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</note>
               <note place="margin">♂ Mars.</note>
               <note place="margin">♀ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enus.</note> and
<note place="margin">☿ Mercury</note>, what Operations they have, is little regarded; whether t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>conjoyned or disjunct, far diſtant from, or near to each other; whether their beams confluentially radiate, or not, whether they be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, or collateral; whether many or few convene in the ſame Houſe, in this or that Sign of the Zodiack,</hi> men paſs not, as all one to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Whereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it comes to paſs that whatſoever ſign the moſt benigne Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vouchſafeth to hold forth in heaven, for the commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and monition of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nkind, is totally made uſeleſs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in.</p>
            <p>HENCE is it that I thought I ſhould do a work worth my labour, for the Glory of God, and the Good of my Neighbours, if I ſhall, as well out of Scripture, as from the na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure of the thing, and the circumſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces thereof, demonſtrate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That ſuch ſorts of Signes do, without all doubt, portend, and foretel ſome grand and ſingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What that is which they portend and foretel;</hi> If perhaps, by the favour of God, ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e from hence may be induced to embrace theſe faithful praemonitions with greater readineſs of mind.</p>
            <p>As for the S. Scriptures;
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.14.</note> In the firſt Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> where is extant the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of he Creation of he Sun, Moon, and other Stars of He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is delivered, that theſe were there placed to that end, <hi>That they might divide the Day from the Night, and be for Signes, and Seaſons, and Dayes, and Yeares.</hi> To wit, that the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42297:3"/>intention of God, when he was about to create theſe Lights was this, that they ſhould ſignifie, and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſhew ſomething on <hi>earth,</hi> which God had before created, <hi>viz.</hi> Not only that they ſhould point out the times of Spring, Summer, Autumn, and Winter, and the ſeaſons of Seed-time, and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rveſt, of planting, and pulling up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> abbreviations, lengthenings, or equalizings of daies; with the Annual Feaſts, Daies, Weeks, and Moneths: <hi>but eſpecially that they might be for ſigns of thoſe things which muſt be acted on earth; and what there, in ſucceſſion of time, as well in the Government of the Church, as of the world ſhould ariſe, and might manifeſt himſelf.</hi> Which thing is intimated by <hi>Moſes</hi> when he ſaith,
<note place="margin">V. 15.</note> 
               <hi>That they may be in the Expanſion of Heaven, to enlighten the earth, i. e.</hi> To give a diſcerning of things to be done on earth. For as for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the <hi>external Light</hi> of the day, that the Sun ſolely ſupplies to us: and for what concernes the Light of the night, the Moon alone would be ſufficient, if nothing elſe were to be deſired. But there ought to be more light preſent with us than that whereby one man by ſight, diſcernes another, one Animal another, and body from body may be diſtinguiſhed. To the end it may be well with man on earth, and the whole Orb of the world below may ſubſiſt, it behoves that there be a certain other ſort of Light, which deſcendeth alſo from on high, and is nouriſhed from above; to wit, a <hi>Rational Light</hi> of diſcerning, and clearneſs of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from whence divers Arts, Sciences, Negotiations, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, as well Eccleſiaſtical, as ſecular, are invented, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to perfection. And that Light is called in the School of Wiſe men <hi>Sideral,</hi> or <hi>Aſtrary,</hi> becauſe it depends upon thoſe Stars of which <hi>Moſes</hi> affirms, <hi>that they were therefore conſtituted in the Expanſion of Heaven, that they may enlighten the world.</hi> And foraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch as this light exiſts firſt in the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vens, (<hi>viz.</hi> in the ſtars and Pranets) before it ſhines on earth, and is there manifeſted; <hi>what wonder, if any man diſcernes the tokens and preludes of thoſe things which are imminent to come to paſs on earth, by the conſtitution of the Heavens</hi> (ſo as he be endued with ſufficient underſtanding:) even as we ſee in a prudent and skilful Phyſiognomiſt, how be is able oft-times to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermine, and foreſee what a man carries in his breaſt, or will bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll him, by his Eyes, Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enance, and Lineaments. But ſome man may ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> If the ſtars are conſtituted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42297:4"/>(ſo) to illuminate the world; how is it that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dehorte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the people from them, when he ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 4.19, 20.</note>, <hi>Take heed leſt thou lift up thine eyes to Heaven, and when thou ſeeſt the Sun, and the Moon, and the Stars, even all the Hoſt of Heaven, ſhouldeſt be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to worſhip them, and ſerve them, Which the Lord thy God hath IMPARTED unto ALL NATIONS under the whole Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But the Lord hath taken you, and brought you forth out of the Iron Furnace, even out of Egypt, to be unto him a people of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> &amp;c. We anſwer, that by this very Text it is clearly evinced, that this obſervation of the Stars is good in it ſelf, and the gift of God. For unleſs it were in it ſelf good and laudable, how could it be ſaid, as it is expreſly here ſaid by <hi>Moſes, That the Lord thy God hath IMPARTED theſe to ALL THE NATIONS under the whole Heaven?</hi> Can it be ſaid indeed that God <hi>imparts</hi> any <hi>evil?</hi> And that to <hi>all Peoples under the whole Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will declare as the very thing is; <hi>whoever he be, that is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to a better and higher matter, he preſently ſlips and prevaricates, as oft as he lets down himſelf to that which is lower.</hi> Foraſmuch therefore as the moſt bountiful God hath revealed himſelf more clearly and nearly to this people, than to any other; ſpeaking to them out of the midſt of the fire, and ſingularly given them holy Laws, and Inſtitutions, as he had not done to any other people; it became them likewiſe to order their lives, not according to the manner of other peoples, who had not received theſe (Lawes) but according to the mode which God of his ſpecial grace had taken care ſhould be declared to them; whereby an <hi>Acceſs</hi> for them unto God himſelf, was in all caſes prepared, ſo as they might be perfectly inſtructed by him. Otherwiſe they would have held it neceſſary to conſult the Sun, Moon or Stars for events, counſels, and direction.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the thing from which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo vehemently dehorteth the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> people, is not, that they attended to the courſe of the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and contemplated the work of Divine Providence in the Heaven: But only they ſhould not ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be driven by them, in bowing before them, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them for Gods, as was wont to be done among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; who attributing to the Stars and Planets, names of Gods, they erected to them Statues, and Temples, and gave them the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42297:4"/>worſhip of Gods. And this they did with ſo great fervency of zeal, that when after a time, by the light of the Goſpel, the fraud of Satan beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to be detected, theſe peoples, by the Faith of Chrut, being accuſed of Idolatry, were ſoon ſet on fire into a huge madneſs. From whence alſo thoſe cruel perſecutions deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their occaſion. But if the Gentiles had not abuſed theſe ceſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Creatures unto evil; If they had ſuffered themſelves to be led, as by the hand, unto God by theſe works of God, as we may ſee it in <hi>Job,</hi> and his <hi>Friends;</hi> and as is ſtill on record to memory in the <hi>Jews</hi> Hiſtoricals the like thing of the ſons of <hi>Seth</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer world; and of <hi>Noah, Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er and preſent world, before the Law was given; And of <hi>Moſes Daniel, Shadrach, Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> under the Law, (of whom it is written
<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 7.22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.4.</note>, that <hi>Moſes was learned in all the wiſdom of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> &amp;c.) As alſo of the <hi>Magi,</hi> living out of the Law, and without the Law;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> legem &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> de gentious.</note> If (I ſay) they had not bowed themſelves before the Hoſt of Heaven, but by this thing they had learned to bow the knee before God the Creator of all things, worſhipping not the <hi>Signes</hi> of future things which he hath ſet before us, but the <hi>hand it ſelf</hi> that put them, <hi>viz.</hi> the Counſel and wiſdom of the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God, verily they had not ſinned; and it would have been far from them to perſecute any man who ſhould attempt to bring them nearer unto God.</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore, that from this dehortation of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (<hi>Deut.</hi> 4.19, 20.) it cannot be concluded, that theſe celeſtial Signes ought not to be obſerved, and attended unto; but only, that we ought not, too much to adhere to them, either to bow down to them, or to worſhip them; or becauſe of them to neglect that which is better, and nearer, as it happened oft in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> through the ſeducements of the world, and of the Prince of the world. Conſult <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.18. and thou ſhalt ſee how the Lord ſhewed to his Prophet what was prepared in the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> viz. <hi>The Children gather wood, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers kindle the fire, and the women knead the dough, to make Cakes to the QUEEN of Heaven</hi> (<hi>Melechet,</hi> that is to the Hoſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) <hi>and to poure out Drink-Offerings unto other Gods.</hi> Yea ſee in <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17, 18. How as well the men as the women of <hi>Judah</hi> did backſlide to that degree of Idolatry, that they brake forth into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42297:5"/>theſe words, <hi>But we will certainly do whatſoever thing goeth out of our own mouth, to burn Incenſe to the QUEEN of Heaven, and to pour out drink offerings unto HER, as we have done, we and our Fathers, our Kings, and our Princes, in the Cities of Judah, and the ſtreets of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, for then had we plenty of victuals, and were well, and ſaw no evil.</hi> So that by <hi>MELECHET,</hi> or the <hi>Queen of Heaven,</hi> they underſtood no other thing but the Hoſt of the Stars; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the thing which the Lord blames in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is not that they gave heed to the Hoſt of Heaven, but that they drew them into abuſe, and Idolatry, doth manifeſtly appear by thoſe things we read in <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.1, 2. Behold, that which in the former Chapter he had expreſſed by the Name of the <hi>Queen of Heaven,</hi> that very ſame here he calleth the <hi>Hoſt of Heaven;</hi> and that which he threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens ſeverely to puniſh in them, is not that they did heedfully conſider the Signes of Heaven, but that they worſhipped them, and bowed themſelves unto them, as unto their Gods.</p>
            <p>There is furthermore another thing, wherein the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> here greatly ſinned, <hi>That to wit, in imitation of the Heathen, they were too much afraid of thoſe Signes of Heaven as if there was not in being a ſuperior power, on which, both they, and all the Hoſt of Heaven did depend: and as if thoſe things which were there prefigured, ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies neceſſarily to attain their affect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> In which reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect the Lord in that manner ſpeakes to them by his Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Learn not the way of the Heathen, and be not diſmayed at the Signes of Heaven, for the Heathen are diſmayed at them.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <q>I have ſet before the Heathen which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve not known me, ſignes in He ven as meanes leading unto me, becauſe they have not known any other way, and have not received any other Law. But <hi>THOU</hi> my people <hi>ISRAEL,</hi> who haſt learned to know me more nearly, and from me haſt received the Law out of the midſt of the fire, which excels all other Laws, return not thou unto the way of the Heathen, but learn thou well the way ſhewn unto thee in my Law, and there ſhall be no cauſe that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of the ſignes of Heaven.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.24, 25.</note> For (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) <hi>I am he which have created the heavens, and have bound my ſelf to thee in an everlaſting and indiſſolvable Covenant. I am JEHOVAH, making all things, extending the heavens alone, spreading abroad the earth by my power, that fruſtrateth the tokens
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42297:5"/>of the Lyars, and maketh the Diviners mad, that turneth the wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Be ye only obedient unto me, walk faithfully in my Wayes, and nothing of thoſe things is to be feared by you, of which the Heathen are afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that we may come nearer to the MATTER; If this were true, that nothing of truth and certainty could be gathered from the celeſtial Signes, and therefore it were prohibited to attend unto them; tell me, I pray thee, <hi>For whom, or what ends are thoſe Signes in the Sun, Moon, and Stars made? To what purpoſe? To what uſe? Why are not only the Jewes in the Old Teſtament
<note n="*" place="margin">Joel 2.30 &amp; 3.15.</note>, but Chriſtians alſo in the New
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24.29. Mar. 13.24. Luk. 21.25.</note> preciſely ſent to them?</hi> as we ſhall hear more largely afterwards. Therefore from the S. Scriptures I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that thoſe ſignes conſpicuous in the Heavens (eſpecially in theſe laſt time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) do neceſſarily portend ſomething, and therefore of right, they are ceſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly and diligently to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object: <hi>Suppoſe that Signes are given in Heaven;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> of thoſe things which ſhall come to paſs on earth, or ought to come to paſs; what doth this he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p me, if I want a requiſite wiſdom to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them? as having no true and undoubted rules, by which I may be able to judge of thoſe Signes?</hi> Doth not the Almigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and moſt exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent God accuſe <hi>Job</hi> of his Ignorance, even in this very buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the predominion of the ſtars on us inhabitants of the earth, asking him by way of opprobry, <hi>Haſt thou known the order of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? wilt thou ſet the dominion thereof on the earth?</hi> As if he had ſaid, Thou knoweſt that thou haſt no knowle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge of this thing; and that thou canſt do nothing in this matter, <hi>Job</hi> 38.33. And doth not <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 25.3. ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k concerning the heavens above us, and the earth beneath us, and the hearts of Kings, that thoſe three are unſearchable; How then ſhall any man dare to attempt, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hout the Note of the greateſt preſumption, ſo to ſearch out thoſe things which are in the Heavens, as thence to pick out, what ſhall come to paſ in the world? And do we not ſee many, yea of the excellenteſt M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſters of Aſtrology greatly to be deceived; as for example, That moſt famous <hi>Albumazar;</hi> of whom we read in his Writings, he foreſaw by the ſtars, that Chriſtian Religion ſhould not continue beyond 1400 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ears from after its firſt be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: whereas to now, ſince Chriſts Birth, we accompt 1662
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42297:6"/>years. Which term exceeds <hi>Albumazars</hi> Calculation, more than 200 years.
<note place="margin">***</note> And there have been afore 142 years ſince, certain Aſtrologers, which from that great Conjunction of (♄) <hi>Saturn,</hi> (♃) <hi>Jupiter</hi> and (♂) <hi>Mars,</hi> in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> which happened in the year of Chriſt 1524, ſtruck a great terrour into men concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome imminent great Deluge (though not univerſal) ſo that many provided themſelves of ſhips, by which, after the manner in <hi>Noahs</hi> Floud, they might ſave themſelves from the Waters; whereas no ſuch thing at all followed thereupon. Many more of the like <hi>Errours</hi> might be produced;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note> but let theſe ſuffice.</p>
            <p>We anſwer; If this be granted, that thoſe things which are ſeen in the Heavens are truly Signes and Preludes of thoſe things which ſhall come to paſs on earth, and for the underſtanding of them, there is need of certain and undoubted Rules and Precepts, to diſcern all things aright: Yet that remaineth firm, and irtefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable, that we are bound to attend to thoſe ſignes, and to apply our minds (as much as in us is) to thoſe premonitions ſet forth in the Heavens, inſtantly to pray for, and expect in faith, greater wiſdom, and underſtanding, as they have done, who ever at tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any certainty in this Science: And moreover to ſet before our eyes, thoſe general Rules which have been delivered to us, by the more skilful in this Art. For, albeit thoſe precepts (partly by the multiplicity, and ſubtilty of them, and partly by the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of a certain ſuperiour cauſe, which can invert, and make void all theſe things) are not alwaies found firm and undoubted: yet if we ſeek of God our certainty, he can equally in theſe, as in other buſineſſes, and Sciences of the world (which conſidered in themſelves are alſo full of uncertainty) eſtabliſh our hearts, and lead us into all certainty of truth: and give to us that we may ſee and diſcern, what others cannot ſee and diſcern.</p>
            <p>As for that place of <hi>Job,</hi> this only is intimated, <hi>If any man will rightly and fundamentally know the order of heaven, and the dominion thereof on the earth he ought to learn it of God, who alone ſetled all theſe things; and therefore it is not meet for Job, or any other man to glory before God.</hi> And for that ſaying of the wiſeſt King, neither doth tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intend any other thing, than to teach us, <hi>That theſe three in themſelves are unſearchable;</hi> to wit, <hi>Heaven,</hi> as being too high and ſublime; the <hi>Earth,</hi> as being too deep; and the <hi>heart of a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42297:6"/>King,</hi> as being too much hidden, unſtable, and mutable. So that from hence it cannot be concluded, that a man that feares God, and cleaves to him, may not be endued, or gifted by God with ſuch wiſdom and underſtanding; that he cannot underſtand the things which are in Heaven above him, and in the earth beneath him, and in the hearts of Kings without him. No by no means. For <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf in the Book of Wiſdom (<hi>Chap.</hi> 7.)
<note place="margin">V. 17.</note> teſtifieth the contrary; where he compileth a Catalogue of thoſe things which he was taught of God, by Wiſdom. <hi>God hath given to me certain or true knowledge of the things that are in Nature, that I might underſtand the conſtitution of the world, the force of the Elements, the beginning, middle and ending of times: the viciſſitudes of Solſtices, the variety of Seaſons, the Circuits of years, and ſituation of ſtars, the natures of Animals, the furies of Beaſts, the ſtrength of the winds, and the cogitations of men: the differences of Plants, and the qualities of Roots.</hi> All theſe, he ſaith, he learned of God, as well thoſe things that are made in Heaven above him, as thoſe in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the earth beneath him; and alſo thoſe things that ſeem to lie hidden in the receſſes of mans heart. <hi>For</hi> (as he addeth, <hi>v.</hi> 21.) <hi>All ſuch things as are ſecret, or manifeſt, them have I known. For Wiſdom which is the Artificer of all things, taught me.</hi> Seeſt thou therefore how all things may be obtained by Wiſdom: as well the knowledge of thoſe things which are in <hi>Heaven,</hi> as thoſe on <hi>Earth,</hi> and in the very <hi>Cloſets of the heart?</hi> Therefore he who hath not this wiſdom, but doth deſire it, let him ask it of God, and ſeek it where it may be found. Neither let him ſay, <q>
                  <hi>What ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageth it me that God hath put certain Signes in Heaven, ſeeing I underſtand them not? and ſo many who have aſſumed to themſelves skill in them, have ſo enormouſly ſtumbled, and expoſed themſelves to ſcorn?</hi>
               </q> For we ſee the ſame things to happen, in all Sciences,
<note place="margin">Orig Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiae.</note> Arts, Negotiations; yea even in <hi>Propheſie,</hi> and the Goſpel, which is called the Word of Truth. Where if one, or another be certain in his Art, and Science, thou ſhalt find ten remaining uncertain. For, where thou maieſt find one true Prophet, with whom there is the ſincere Word of God, there an hundred will preſent themſelves; who challenge to themſelves the ſame word, and carry before, them, in external geſture, and habit, the ſhew or ſhape of a Prophet, when as they are not. And where thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42297:7"/>ſhalt find one who purely delivers the word of Truth, thou maieſt muſter up an hundred who wreſt it to the private ſence of humane corruption. Are therefore all Arts and Sciences to be deſpiſed, and to be accompted and reputed in the ſame rank as we ſee at this day, the Celeſtial Signes reputed? Certainly if this were ſo, there were an end of all Science, Art, Propheſie, and all Doctrine of Truth. And all things, as uncertain and dead, muſt be buried in the profound darkneſs of Ignorance and Confuſion, and there eternally lie buried. Thou ſeeſt therefore, that for the dotages or miſtakes of ſome in the knowledge of Aſtrology, and falſly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging to themſelves the knowledge of the underſtanding of the Celeſtial Signes, all Obſervation of the ſtars, and Prognoſtications are not by and by to be vilified.</p>
            <p>But let us proceed to the ſecond Member of this our Diſſerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that by the nature it ſelf of the <hi>Conjunction</hi> we may demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, That neceſſarily ſome grand, and ſingular thing is here portended. That therefore thou maieſt better perceive the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this <hi>Conjunction,</hi> or concurrence of all the Planets in one and the ſame Sign of the Zodiack, take this ſimilitude: <hi>Whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we ſee all the Rulers in any City,
<note place="margin">An apt Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aile.</note> or Commanders in an Army of Souldiers, convent in one place, and there take counſel together; preſently we thence conclude, ſome grand thing is in agitation: The ſame thing therefore may be here concluded, when we ſee the Planets ſo convent and lay their heads together.</hi> For look what the Rulers in a City, and Commanders in an Hoſt are; the ſame are the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in the Hoſt of Heaven. Other ſtars in the Firmament conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in their fixed diſtances one from the other, and have no pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar motion, as every one of the Planets hath his own proper motion, each wheeled about in his own ſphere, after his own manner. Therefore ancient wiſe men conſidering the Analogy or proportion between the (Macrocoſme) the <hi>great</hi> world, and the (Microcoſme) the <hi>little</hi> world, ſaid, by the fixed ſtars of the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament were repreſented the <hi>firm Limbs</hi> of out body; and by the Planets our <hi>inward bowels,</hi> which by their motion, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, move, ſuſtain, and act the whole body. What wonder then, if we beholding of <hi>December</hi> next
<note n="*" place="margin">1. 1662. For <hi>Serari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> wrote this afore the ſaid day of <hi>December</hi> laſt.</note> the Members of the greater world, as the Rulers of the Aethereal, and Elementary Orbs, convening in one and the ſame houſe, laying their heads
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42297:7"/>together, we conclude that doubtleſs ſome grand thing is to be agitated in the Heavens, which is in a readineſs that unexpectedly it may break forth? And that by ſo much more certainly, by how much we have been taught by long experience, that as often as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Planets come together, they alwaies bring forth ſome notable change on earth.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, when the two ſupreme Regents of the world (♄) <hi>Saturn</hi> and (♃) <hi>Jupiter</hi> concur, or come together; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed manifeſtly appeares to be done three waies. Their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſure or coming together <hi>the firſt way, is every twentieth year,</hi> or in preciſe ſpeech, <hi>within the ſpace of</hi> 19 <hi>years, daies</hi> 315, <hi>houres</hi> 19. And is called by Aſtrologers the <hi>ſpecial,</hi> or <hi>leaſt</hi> Conjunction of (♄) <hi>Saturn,</hi> and (♃) <hi>Jupiter,</hi> becauſe Saturn and Jupiter concur in the ſignes of the ſame triplicity. Their congreſſure or meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together <hi>the ſecond way, is every</hi> 200 <hi>years,</hi> or in preciſe ſpeech, once <hi>within</hi> 198 <hi>years, and</hi> 336 <hi>daies.</hi> And is called the <hi>Trigonal,</hi> or <hi>middle</hi> Conjunction, whereby the ſame Planets (♄ and ♃) <hi>i. e. Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> concur, or meet, in another Triplicity, or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon
<note n="*" place="margin">Orig. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonum.</note>. Their Concurrence <hi>the third way, returnes not under</hi> 800 <hi>yeares:</hi> or in preciſe accompt, <hi>after the term of</hi> 795 <hi>years and</hi> 214 <hi>daies.</hi> And is called the <hi>greatest,</hi> and <hi>total</hi> Conjunction. Which comes to paſs when (♄ and ♃) <hi>i.e. Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> having wandred over all the Triplicities, return to the ſame Goal or Bound; from whence they firſt ſet forth.</p>
            <p>And although upon all theſe 3 modes of Conjunctions of the ſupream Planets (♄ and ♃) <hi>Saturn and Jupiter,</hi> alwaies ſome ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Changes in the world have followed; yet notwithſtanding, they alwaies have by far been of the greateſt moment, which have followed the <hi>Great</hi> Conjunctions or <hi>Congreſſures of the third way or mode.</hi> For example,
<note place="margin">☜</note> From the Fall of <hi>Adam</hi> there have been 7 of theſe <hi>Great</hi> Conjunctions: Or if with <hi>Kepler</hi> and other the moſt famous Aſtrologers we may annumerate alſo the <hi>Firſt,</hi> in the very beginning of the world, then from that time, to our age are numbred 8 of that ſort of Conjunctions. For, the firſt is numbered in the time of <hi>Adam,</hi> upon which followed the Fall of all Mankind. The ſecond in the time of <hi>Enoch,</hi> which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with Tyranny, Robberies, building of Fortifications, and walled Townes. 3. In <hi>Noahs</hi> time; which was entertained
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42297:8"/>by the Deluge of waters, whereby tranſgreſſors were blotted out from the face of the earth. 4. In the life of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Which was welcomed in by the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Law, and the riſe of the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Canaan.</hi> The fifth in the daies of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> upon which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1. The tranſportation of the 10 Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> into the Land of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> (who to this day have not returned) and anon after that, of the two Tribes <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin;</hi> from whence, nevertheleſs, after 70 years Captivity they did return. 6. From the time of Chriſt, which was accompanied and followed by the riſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and the total deſtruction of the <hi>Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Commonwealth. 7. From the Age of <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> upon which followed the Diviſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, into Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern and Weſtern; as alſo the Invaſion of the <hi>Turk,</hi> into the land of Promiſe, and that Reformation ſprung up in the Church, whereby the Kingdom of the Apocalyptical Beaſt began to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured.</p>
            <p>Theſe things therefore being thus weighed,
<note place="margin">N.B.</note> what notable Changes theſe 7 former Conjunctions have brought into the world, when nevertheleſs they conſiſted but of the concurſe only of two or three Planets; how can it be otherwiſe judged, but that neceſſarily a greater change is portended under the eighth great Conjunction of them (which happened in the year of Chriſt) 1603. in <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> under which we yet travel in pain, and ſob. And ſo much the rather, that <hi>this
<note n="*" place="margin">By <hi>This,</hi> I ſuppoſe he means this <hi>Decemb.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>/11 <hi>Anno</hi> of Chr. 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. of which he treats, and by <hi>That,</hi> he means that in 1603.</note> concurrence</hi> of all the Planets in the ſame fiery Sign of <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> followed <hi>that</hi> in ſo ſhort a time. For my part, thoſe thoughts I confeſs, ſpring up within me, <hi>That even as anciently in the Feaſts of Iſrael, and their great Solemnities, which laſted eight daies, it was cautioned that the laſt day was alwaies to be reputed for the greateſt day, with which the Feaſt was concluded</hi> (Levit. 23.36. John 7.37.) <hi>So alſo do I judge in this matter, that of all theſe</hi> 8 <hi>great Conjunctions, this laſt is to be accompted for the greateſt:</hi> After which, there is nothing more certain to follow, than the Period of <hi>Eſaus</hi> time, and the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Beaſts Dominion, and falſe Prophet; <hi>That now at laſt the time of Jacob may ſucceed, and the Kingdom of JESUS CHRIST and of his Saints may be eſtabliſhed on Earth.</hi> For if ſome greater thing is hence to be expected, than ever any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42297:8"/>afore produced, what other thing can this be, than the Reſtitution of that Kingdom ſo long promiſed, and deſired, and which the Apoſtles themſelves expected by Chriſt to be erected, (<hi>Acts</hi> 1.5.) and the final ruine of the Kingdomes of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this world? that another world may ſucceed, whoſe Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may be meet for God only, and to him aſcribed.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>the third great Conjunction</hi> (aforeſaid) the former <hi>world</hi> periſhed, and <hi>another</hi> came forth, as if called up from the dead. <hi>At the fourth Conjunction</hi> the Lord choſe to himſelf one only Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, out of all the peoples that had in this new world corrupted themſelves, which he brought out of the houſe of <hi>Egyptian</hi> bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and brought them into a certain Land where he himſelf would govern them. <hi>At the Fifth Conjunction,</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the ſins of that people, was cleft and parted into two Kingdoms, of which, one was tranſported into <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to this day; the other into <hi>Babylon,</hi> for a little time. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Sixth Conjunction,</hi> followed the diſperſion of them alſo which returned from <hi>Babylon,</hi> which continues to this day through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Provinces of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Upon the <hi>Seventh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction,</hi> this very laſt Monarchy of the <hi>Romans</hi> underwent the ſame Lot as the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuffered. For as this was firſt divided, and afterwards one part of it after another was torn and carried away: So this laſt Monarchy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was firſt divided into Eaſtern and Weſtern, the firſt whereof the <hi>Turks</hi> now long ſince have invaded, and poſſeſſed. And what now I pray can remain to be expected, upon this 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Conjunction,</hi> but that the remnant-part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire have the ſame fate as ancient <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had. Truly if we conſult the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, that grand and general mutation, which we, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do expect, and is to be expected, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be no other than that <hi>in the room of the preſent Kingdoms of the world, the God of Heaven will ſet up a Kingdom,
<note place="margin">N.B.</note> which ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate all other Kingdomes,</hi> (Dan. 2.44.) <hi>And that terrible Beaſt of</hi> Daniel, <hi>to wit, the fourth Monarchy of the world, which hath tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den underfoot, broken, and crummed the whole Earth into morſels; and that little and blasphemous horn, ſhall likewiſe at length, being brought to Judgment, be deprived of their Dominion, and utterly deſtroyed: So that at laſt, the Kingdom, and the Power, and the greatneſs of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42297:9"/>the Kingdom which is under the whole Heaven, is given to the holy people of the Most High,</hi> &amp;c. (Dan. 7.26, 27.) To wit, this is that change which we Chriſtians with ourſtretched neck do expect, <hi>that ſhortly it ſhall comes to paſs that the ſcattering of the holy people, ſhall have an end</hi> (Dan. 12.7.) <hi>that ere long the Redeemer comes out of Sion, who ſhall take away infidelity from Jacob,</hi> (Rom. 11.26.) <hi>And that voice of that ſtrong Angel (who by his gloriouſneſs ſhall brighten the whole earth) ſhall ring over the whole world, ſaying, Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul Spirit, and the Cage of every unclean, and hareful Bird.</hi> Rev. 18.1, 2. What (I ſay) is it, that we Chriſtians ſince once the Kingdom of the Beaſt hath been obſcured, do ſo anxiouſly deſire, and in all our Prayers petition for, than <hi>that at length</hi> the ſixth Vial alſo, may be poured out upon the <hi>River EUPHRATES, that the way for the Kings that are to come from the Eaſt may be prepared,</hi> (<hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12.) to wit, for the KINGS, of which <hi>Baruch</hi> ſpeaks, (<hi>ch.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 5.) <hi>Ariſe O Jeruſalem, and ſtand on high, and look towards the Eaſt, and behold thy Children gathered from the weſt, unto the eaſt, by the word of the holy One, rejoycing in the remembrance of God. For they departed from thee on foot, and were led away of their enemies. But God bringeth them unto thee, exalted with Glory, as children of the Kingdom.</hi> And after theſe things, what elſe do we expect, but that <hi>the Kings of the Earth, and all their hoſts, be by thoſe impure Spirits</hi> (Rev. 16.13. <hi>like to Frogs</hi>) <hi>excited, and gathered together to the war of that great day of God Almighty,</hi> (Rev. 16.4. Iſa. 13.) <hi>in which God ſhall ariſe and go down into the valley of Jehoſaphat,</hi> and there <hi>ſhall judge the people, and that Nation which hath hitherto ſo miſerably broken and troden underfoot the diſperſed ſheep of Iſrael,</hi> (Joel 3.2, 12.) and that he may utterly and for ever blot our, and <hi>extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Babylon, that great City, the Mother of the Fornications of the Earth, that terrible, and blaſphemous Beaſt, and Falſe-Prophet,</hi> (Rev. 18, &amp; 19.) Behold, that concerning theſe Changes, not only the old Prophets, but the Lord himſelf, JESUS CHRIST, and his Apoſtles do witneſs. And whoever is not blind, but a little exerciſed in the S. Script. and experience of former Ages, and this preſent, it will be eaſie for him to collect, that now all theſe things neceſſarily are at hand, by and by to be expected. <hi>Therefore it ought to ſeem a wonder to no man; that theſe Celeſtial Signes</hi> (which neceſſarily
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42297:9"/>fortel the Tidings of ſome grand and eminent univerſal change) <hi>are referred, or applyed by us, to this matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet that it may more clearly appear, that this preſent Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all the Planets, is with great equity to be ſo interpreted by us; go to, let us turn our ſelves to the Planets themſelves: and let us, I pray thee, contemplate the Conſtitution and Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe <hi>Peers</hi> of Heaven, and <hi>Regents</hi> of the world; how their countenances are found diſpoſed, both towards us, and one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, in this their unuſual Congreſſure, or coming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For the <hi>Countenance,</hi> as it is commonly given forth, <hi>is the Index of the mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the POSTURE of theſe Regents, thou ſhalt find them all, to be complexionated with a troubled, and ſad countenance. To wit, thou ſhalt ſee the <hi>Moon,</hi> newly departed from the beams of the Sun (from whom ſhe was gone ſcarce 7 degrees) to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently enflamed, all fiery, and burning, by the corporal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Mars:</hi> and that ſo much the more, in that <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf is more enflamed by the conjunction of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the Sun takes his turn to be made more hurtful and diſcontented by the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn.</hi> To which is added, that <hi>Mercury,</hi> which with the good is good, and with the bad is bad, is here <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily become the worſt with the worſt.</hi> For he being corporally joyned with <hi>Saturn,</hi> what elſe will he bring forth by his Influences in this univerſal Combuſtion, but all manner of fallacies, frauds, betrayings, filling all with ſiniſter ſuſpitions, ſecret Conſpiracies, and inteſtine hatreds, and ſo fulfilling, or filling up the meaſure of all unrighteouſneſs, and violence on earth. Whilſt <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> (whoſe Houſe this is) although alſo preſent, yet ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, will be ſo hindred and obſtructed by the combuſtion, and malignity of the intercurrent Planets, that they will not be able with their more benigne beams (while as ſtrangers they invaded anothers Houſe) to reach unto us. And if that be true, that <hi>Theodorus Hoen,</hi> a Famous Aſtrologer affirmeth, and others alſo, teſtifie to be certainly collected from the Tables of Conjunctions of Planets, <hi>that in the time of Noah, there was the like conjunction of all the Planets in PISCES, awatery Sign,</hi> upon which followed that terrible Judgment of an univerſal Deluge, which together at once blotted out all the wicked, from the face of the earth: why
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42297:10"/>may it not be lawful for us to collect from this concurſe of all the Planets in the fiery Sign <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> that by it <hi>is portended and foretold that fiery Judgment which immediately foreruns the Kingdom of Chriſt; intimated in</hi> Peter (<hi>Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.) <hi>and in the</hi> Revelation, (<hi>ch.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 18.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. If thou conſider the PLACE, in which all thoſe Aethereal Regents convene, thou wilt find it to be the ſame, wherein the late great Conjunction in the year 1603, the 29th. day of <hi>Sept.</hi> or 9 of <hi>Oct.</hi> was acted, under which we ſtill labour; its full and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal operation being not yet at an end: to wit, <hi>the last Sign of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitarius in the fiery Trigon.</hi> As if the Heavens, which are ſaid to declare the glory of God, and his Juſtice (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.) did by their voice intend no other than to repeat that ſignification of the next preceding great Conjunction, and by a ſecond Proclamation to confirm unto us, that this combuſtion is no other then that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this preſent world of the wicked ſhall be burnt. For if this be true, that the preſent world ſhall ſhortly periſh by fire, and that Signes thereof are by God placed in Heaven; it is neceſſary that this Sign be ſome fiery one, which may moſt aptly ſquare with the expreſſion of this ſignification. And if the Sign ought to be a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, it muſt be this, which is the third and laſt, in which alſo the great preceding, and laſt Conjunction was acted. And that which is more, and more commends this <hi>place</hi> of the Heaven is, that the very next day after the ſaid Conjunction, <hi>Sept.</hi> 30. or <hi>Oct.</hi> 10. 1603. when now by the coming of <hi>Mars,</hi> that great Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction had received its compleatment, that fame <hi>New Star</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Serpentario,</hi> preciſely in the ſame place of Heaven, on which all the Aſtrologers eyes were fixed, expecting the Conjunction of (♄ and ♂) <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> witneſs <hi>Kepler,</hi> in the Book which he wrote concerning the New Star in <hi>Serpentario,</hi> of which he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth many, and wonderful things. I will here add one out of the ſaid Book, where the Author comparing this <hi>Star</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>This Star, i. e.</hi> that 1603.</note> with that which was ſeen in <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> in the year 1573, ſaith thus: <q>
                  <hi>THAT FORMER
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Former. Orig. prior illa,</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to that ſtar, <hi>Anno</hi> 1573. And <hi>Later</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to that 1603. as I underſtand <hi>Sed caveat Lector.</hi>
                     </note> cometh on the world unpremoniſhed, and as an unlookt for enemy, which having poſſeſt the City wals, appeared in the Market place afore the Citizens had heard the fame of his Expedition. But this LATTER being long time afore expected, entred at the appointed day, with great ſolemnity, after the manner
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42297:10"/>of ſome mighty Monarch, who about to viſit his Metropolitan City, ſending afore him his Quarter-maſters, deſigneth places to all the Princes of his Court. Now the Waies or Streets are cleanſed; now the common people upon the rumour of the Army, run to and fro; now the Boyes complain of the delay of his coming, whilſt the fardels and houſhold-ſtuffe are brought in. By and by his retinue following, while the firſt enter the gates, and the noiſe of them, and ſound of Drums pierceth all the high waies; all perſons being allarm'd, they fill the Windowes, crowd the Streets, and the little Boyes and young Girles are ſtartled with joy, the high Heroes and faithful Miniſters ride on her ſeback; the common people gaze with open mouth, and wiſhly look on every one, as greedy to behold the King. At last, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the long Train, appeares the Troop of Drummers and Trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; after which followes the awful rank of Armed men, on each ſide whereof there is a file of Curriers; in the midſt is the KING, curvetting or prancing on a generous Horſe, Glorious in Purple or Scarlet, and Gold. There needs not the pointing of Fingers, or ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Queſtions, every one, having ſeen the Guard, ſaith in his own private breaſt, Behold now at laſt him whom thou haſt deſired.</hi>
               </q> What meant this quick-ſighted Author, in ſo prolix, and elegant a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of this Star, but that he might ſet before our eyes, the Majeſty of him that is ſignified thereby? to wit, that Glorious <hi>Advent</hi> of the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> whom all, and every where the Creatures, eſpecially the Inhabitants of his <hi>Metropolis</hi> (the men of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) have, as with out-ſtretched neck ſo long expected. To which purpoſe it advantageth, that the ſaid <hi>Keplerus</hi> affirmeth, that this Star almoſt in all circumſtances is like to that which the <hi>wiſe men</hi> ſaw in the Eaſt, as the Sign of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> King of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> excepting this Stars <hi>Immobility,</hi> and <hi>Altitude.</hi> See <hi>Kepler</hi> in the ſaid Book, <hi>p.</hi> 134, 135. To wit, this in <hi>Serpeutario,</hi> ſtood unmoveable in the Firmament; That of the wiſe men moved in the inferiour sky. The other was in the ſuperiour, this in the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour part of Heaven. Whereby it ſeemeth, not obſcurely to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated that <hi>this Star,</hi> as it looked at none other than that ſame <hi>King of the Jews,</hi> ſo it was the Harbenger of an higher, <hi>and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Kingdom,</hi> than ever yet Chriſt had, or hitherto hath been known to the world. Seeing theſe things are ſo (that namely, the place in which this year
<note n="*" place="margin">He means <hi>laſt year,</hi> viz. 1662.</note> is the meeting of all the Planets, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42297:11"/>to be one and the ſame, with that place wherein 59 years ſince, was beheld not only that great Conjunction, but alſo that new Royal Star in <hi>Serpentarie,</hi> and of ſome called the <hi>Sign of the Son of man</hi>) what other thing I pray can be collected (if any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit may be give to the works of God) then this, that this congreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<note n="*" place="margin">of 1602.</note> or coming together, hath reſpect unto the ſame thing of which we moniſhed but now, concerning that great Conjunction, and new Star.</p>
            <p>To the CIRCUMSTANCES of this <hi>Synod</hi> (of Stars) will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the conſideration of the TIME, in which it <hi>begins, continues,</hi> and <hi>ends.</hi> It <hi>begins</hi> with the entrance of <hi>Jupiter</hi> to the reſt already congregated; which is done in the night preceding that 1/12 day of <hi>December:</hi> and is ended by the Moons going out again, in the night immediately following: ſo that the <hi>Duration</hi> of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, is not beyond one day, which alſo is indeed ominous. For as if thou ſhalt ſee the States of a City, or Commanders of an Army, ſolemnly congregated, ſuddenly and tremulouſly again de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part one from another, there is none but would thence gather, that there is ſome great matter in that thing: even ſo it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this matter; whilſt thoſe Captaines of the Celeſtial bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that have fcarcely once met for ſo many Ages, ſhould ſo ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily again haſten away from each other, may they not juſtly ſtrike a terrour? For they are aſſembled together in that common Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of the Celeſtial <hi>Sagitarius</hi> out of our ſight, in a place ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneous to us in <hi>Europe,</hi> in the night time (we being deeply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep) and ſo are carried up as in one Chariot above our Horizon, and born away beyond our vertical South point, and by the Weſt tranſported out of our ſight, and ſo begin again to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</p>
            <p>But <hi>how are they ſeparated?</hi> Which of them all firſt goes forth? The <hi>Moon,</hi> which by any means, by her ſwift motion among the Stars acting the part of a Currier, or Poſt, is firſt diſmiſſed, that it may carry about ſwift tidings to the whole world. Yea becauſe ſhe is the Receptacle and Chariot of all the Celeſtial Influences, and the ſlinger out of them upon the world, it cauſeth a beginning of unuſual operations, <hi>i. e.</hi> It poureth forth the efficacy of thoſe beams which had been collected in the common Conjunction. After which, after 5 daies followes enflamed <hi>Mars,</hi> the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42297:11"/>of heat, or wrath and fury, yet fuming. Next after the <hi>Sun,</hi> follows <hi>Venus,</hi> after other 10 daies, to wit, the 30th. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> And again after nine daies <hi>Mercury</hi> (<hi>January</hi> 8.) Only ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant <hi>Saturn</hi> being left alone in the Houſe of <hi>Juplter</hi> to contend with benign <hi>Jupiter</hi> for a whole year, when or at which time, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> being weary of ſtriving, is driven out of his own houſe, betakes himſelf to <hi>Capricorn, Anno</hi> 1664, <hi>Jan.</hi> 3. <hi>Saturn</hi> abiding behind in his place aforeſaid, above 11 moneths (to the 16 of <hi>Decemb.</hi>) But there will come to paſs yet, two notable Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the ſame fiery Sign of <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">N.B.</note> The faſt is of <hi>Jupiter</hi> with <hi>Saturn, Oct.</hi> 21. 1663. The ſecond of <hi>Mars</hi> with <hi>Saturn, Novemb.</hi> 22. 1664; all which (if any credit to Heaven) being the worſt of ominous Tokens, ſeem to be the foretellers of terrible Confuſions, Perturbations, Wars and Slaughters on earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo many fatal periods of things every where in the world fall in together.</p>
            <p>The ANTECEDENTS, which went before this Seſſion of theſe Rulers of the world, and are ſuch a ſign of ſome grand and ſingular thing to be noted thereby, are <hi>theſe</hi> (beſides what we but now premiſed concerning that great Conjunction and new Star.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>terrible Comet,</hi> which about the end of Autumn in the year 1618, expoſed it ſelf to be beheld, formidable for its Tayle, or flaming wand. The chaſtiſements of which Rod, even to this day leave the whole body of the Church, ſickly, and as in an Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, full of wounds, and malignant Ulcers, whoſe Corruption is not yet wrought out, nor the pain mitigated. 2. <hi>Another Comet</hi> appeared in the year 1652. And again a <hi>third</hi> in the year 1659, near the <hi>Celeſtial Aquila,</hi> or Eagle, not drawing a flaming Tayl af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, like the reſt, but on its forehead was a fiery Dart, brandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were its forked head like a ſting, making at the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides Comets, which are to us as publick Heralds of things ſignified to us by the ſolemn meetings of thoſe Celeſtial Regents, how many <hi>wonderful (Phaenomena)</hi> Appearances in the Air have been ſeen, for ſome years laſt paſt? <hi>What Armies in the Heavens? What Conflicts in the Air? What concertations of Ships, men of War, daſhing themſelves one againſt another, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42297:12"/>each other with Fire and Sword? Who is able to recite, how many Monſters, and Prodigies, as well in Heaven, as on the Earth, and Sea have been ſeen,</hi> (<hi>ſince the laſt Conjunction</hi> 1603 <hi>came forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage?) what terrible Tempests, and unheard of Blaſts of winds</hi> have been, whereby not only innumerable Ships have been bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at Sea, but Trees have been eracicated out of the Earth, and high Towers caſt down. But I ſpeak what I know happened a year or two ſince at <hi>Roſtoch,</hi> whoſe Tower, though covered, or crampt with Braſs, was cut a two, as it were with a Sword, and carried away as if with hands, without the wals. How many, and how great Earthquakes to be trembled at, ſince that, as well in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> as <hi>France,</hi> and elſewhere have happened; with which many men as in a moment, have been ſwallowed up, yea whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yea whole Iſlands drowned, or overwhelmed with Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains (as <hi>Pluyrs</hi> in <hi>Rhetia,</hi> in the year 1618.) How many ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den burnings have been ſeen here and there ſince that, whoſe ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal no man knows? Yea how many have been, of which it is manifeſt they were ſent from the Heavens, as by common fame happened in certain places in <hi>Germany,</hi> in the Territories of <hi>Cleve,</hi> and in other Regions. Out of <hi>Galata,</hi> a City ſituated not far from <hi>Constantinople,</hi> I ſaw it written, that in the flame with which the City was burning, were ſeen evil Spirits, driving for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Flame. What rage of Famine occaſioned by the dearth and want of Proviſion, hath waſted throughout the whole body of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; whereby Mothers were made to devour their own Off-ſpring, and friend to kill his friend, that he might eat his fleſh; yea and the bodies of the dead were taken up out of the graves, that the barking ſtomack might be ſatiated. If I would relate what prodigious things came to paſs in earth and Heaven during the bloudy War of <hi>Germany, Poland, England, Swedland,</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> I ſhould be too prolix or tedious, and perhaps more ungrateful to tender years. Of thoſe things only, which happened in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> within the ſpace of one year, there is a whole Book extant, under the name of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis Annus,</hi> &amp;c. which were ſeen in Heaven and in Earth within the year 1660. And if there ſhould be ſet before our eyes what Monſters have come forth from the time of the laſt Conjunction, as well among Bruits, as men, it would be horrid to hear them,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42297:12"/>and unſafe for women great with child to read them. Only this one will I declare, of which I have undoubted certainty; to wit, that in <hi>Tannum,</hi> a City in <hi>Norway,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Wenſuſſel,</hi> about the Kalends of <hi>January,</hi> 1661, there was an Infant born, which was heard to cry in his Mothers womb 12 times, <hi>Woe to Denmarke, Woe to the whole world,</hi> Therefore all theſe things which we have ſeen to follow the laſt Conjunction, and now alſo to precede before the concutrence of the Planets in the ſame place, are a demonſtration to me, that of neceſſity ſome grand, and ſingular things hereby are ſignified, even ſuch things as I have but now noted.</p>
            <p>But ſome man may perhaps ſay, <hi>It is not a thing ſo paſt remedy and given for gone, as is preſumed by us. The Conjunction of all the Planets is not a matter ſo unwonted and rare, that it ſhould ſeem to portend a fiery judgment, as that Conjunction in the time of</hi> Noah <hi>portended the deluge.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe (as <hi>Seth Calviſius</hi> in his Chronological work doth teſtifie) there was obſerved alſo a Conjunction of all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in the year of Chriſt 1186, <hi>Sept.</hi> 16, the third day of the week, the firſt hour of the Day; upon which notwithſtanding, no ſuch, or the like thing followed.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer; That reaſon is not ſufficient to break the force of our Argument: 1. <hi>Becauſe that Conjunction of</hi> 1186, <hi>although it fell within the bounds of a Conjunction, yet was it not in one Sign, as is ours, but in diverſe Signes:</hi> the great Luminaries being in <hi>Virgo,</hi> and the reſt of the Planets in <hi>Libra.</hi> 2. Becauſe that Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in 1186 being in an earthy, and ayry Sign, muſt neceſſarily be meeker than this in a fiery Sign, or than that in a watery ſign in <hi>Noahs</hi> time. 3. Leſt notwithſtanding, any man ſhould repute that Conjunction in 1186 to be of no moment, let him conſult the Hiſtories of 1186, and he ſhall ſee, that by and by, in the year following it, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was taken by <hi>Saladine</hi> the King of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and that <hi>New Jeruſalemitiſh Kingdom</hi> was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Chriſtians. Nor were there wanting other horrid things. The Sea in <hi>Sicilia,</hi> contrary to its Nature went back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to the drowning of 5 millions of men. In <hi>Italy</hi> it rained Hailſtones of the bigneſs of Gooſe Eggs. <hi>Carina</hi> a City of <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> was ſwallowed of an Earthquake; and in that 20 thouſand men periſhed. Alſo a fiery Beam was ſeen in the Heavens, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42297:13"/>other portentous things of that nature. So that that Conjunction alſo, departed not, without ſome notable operation or effect, as well in the air, as in the earth. 4. Let men know that we do not put the whole ſtreſs of our Prognoſtication in the naked Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For unleſs Antecedents, Concomitants, and Subſequents, founded as well in S. Scripture, as in experience, did add weight to the thing, we ſhould not write theſe things with ſuch confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Let us now therefore come to CONCOMITANTS, from whence may be concluded, at leaſt probably, concerning the end of this world, and the imminent approach of the future. Verily, I do not think it lightly to be eſteemed, that care is ſo taken by the providence of the all-fore-ſeeing, and fore-diſpoſing God, that on the day preceding this Conjunction, <hi>viz. December</hi> 10. ſhould fall the Lords day of the 2 <hi>Advent.</hi> wherein are thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.25. <hi>And then ſhall be ſigns in the Sun, and Moon, and Stars, and upon the earth diſtreſs of Nations, with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, the Sea and the waves roaring, mens hearts failing them for fear; and for looking after thoſe things which are coming on earth; for the powers of Heaven ſhall be ſhaken. And then ſhall they ſee the Son of man coming in a cloud, with power, and great glory.</hi> As if that our bleſſed God, to whom all his waies are known from eternity, had, beſides this concurrence of the Planets, and agitations of the celeſtial powers, expreſly commanded that alſo this Propheſie and exhortation of the Lord Jeſus, ſhould be read of all, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated, preciſely on that very day which immediatly goes afore that Conjunction, if perhaps yet in this laſt moment of time, ſome would conſider, and uſe means to be ſaved.</p>
            <p>See now, we have given it forth, demonſtrated both out of the S. Scriptures, as alſo from the nature of the thing, and divers both antecedent, and concomitant circumſtances, <hi>That theſe coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial ſignes do neceſſarily portend ſome great and ſingular thing ſome mighty change, as well in the Civil, as the Eccleſiaſtical Government.</hi> And for as much as, according to the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and the conſtitution of the Time wherein we live, no ſingular thing yet remains to be fulfilled, but that the <hi>Jewes may be converted unto Chriſt; and incidently that Babylon comes into remembrance before God, and all the wicked, by the fire of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42297:13"/>be blotted out of the earth, whereby all the Kingdoms of the world may be made obedient unto God and Chriſt;</hi> we juſtly conclude hence, that all theſe very ſame things are prefigured and portend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, by all the aforeſaid celeſtial ſignes afore recited. And therefore we ought ſeriouſly to watch, and diligently to weigh with our ſelves how the matter ſtands in us with God and our neighbour. <hi>Whether our loynes are girt, our lamps burning?
<note place="margin">N.B.</note> That in ſuch poſture we expect the coming of our Lord to the marriage, and that ſo ſoon as ever he ſhall come, and knock, we preſently open to him the door,</hi> Luk. 12.35, 36. I ſay, <hi>Whether our lamps be trimmed,</hi> that at whatſoever hour that cry ſhall ring out, <hi>Behold, the Bridegroom cometh,</hi> we forthwith be prepared to meet him. If not, but in the abſence of our Lord we are found to have dealt perfidiouſly, have acted ſtrifes and contentions, eaten and drunk with the drunken, have fallen into a Lethargy of ſloath and negligence, and ſo have profoundly and deeply ſlept. What remedy then? How then ſhall we hide our ſelves from the wrath of the Lamb, and from the face of ſo faithful a Maſter, and Bridegroom, who ſo dearly bought us, and did ſo ſtraitly charge us to wait for his return to the Marriage? What ſhall we anſwer unto him who hath ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and continually forewarned us by ſo many, and ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of his moſt Sacred word, and by ſo many, and ſo great ſigns in the Heavens?</p>
            <p>But I ſeem to hear the voice of ſome moſt famous men, and exerciſed or experienced in Aſtronomicals, objecting, <hi>'Tis true, that the Planets do by their Influences act upon theſe inferior bodies, as certain general cauſes; but ſeeing the actions of men, and their Effects, and Conſequences are not determined by thoſe general cauſes, but by theſe particular</hi> (to wit, by mans will, and the free conſults of men) <hi>it were fond, and beſide ſound reaſon, to intend to conclude any thing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain concerning the Actions of men, and their effects and conſequences, by thoſe general Influences of the Planets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe things I Anſwer, 1. <hi>We determine nothing concerning the Actions of men, and their Effects and Conſequences by the Stars, as by their CAUSES, but only as by the SIGNES of them.</hi> Whereby God doth foreſhew us, and ſet before our eyes as in a Table the freeſt Actions of men, and their Effects and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences: For as God foreſaw all things which ſhould ever come
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42297:14"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o paſs, from the firſt beginning of the world (as it appears plainly out of the Propheſies of <hi>Daniel,</hi> (chap. 2. 20.) and of other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; ſo hath he ſet the Signes of all theſe things in the Heavens, that they who have eyes to ſee, might there ſee as in a Looking-Glaſs, what God hath foreſeen ſhall come to paſs on earth in his time. 2. <hi>In that we ſeem here to determine ſomthing as certain, we have not that, from the Stars, but from the S. Scriptures, probable Reaſon, and by a certain ſenſitive experience.</hi> All which, ſeeing they do ſo fairly agree with the Stars, and concur to the ſame ſenſe, they deſervedly ought to be of ſome moment with us.</p>
            <p>But <hi>grant that thou canſt not know certainly any thing, by thoſe Celeſtial Signes, as being above thee, and exceed thy capacity;</hi> If neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou haſt thine eyes open to ſee what things are done on earth, and thine ears to hear what the Sacred Scripture doth expreſly and roundly teach, there will not be wanting to thee Reaſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou maiſt ſufficiently diſcern, the end of this world, and the beginning of the next at hand. For which there is no need of ſpiritual eyes, and ſublime underſtanding, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut only of attentive obſervation of things viſible, and ſenſible, and humane Faith only, whereby we ſo believe the Signes incurring into our eyes, that we be convinced. For who doth not ſee how the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world is divided in it ſelf, and miſerably torn into many contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry parties? Even as the <hi>Secular</hi> Government, or laſt Monarchy of the world? And which is more, <hi>how not only the whole is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two integral and great parts (as of old) but into many little ſmall parts;</hi> and again every Part, every Sect, every Region, and Nation, diſagree among themſelves, ſo that the people know not which way to turn, nor whom they may believe. One <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick riſeth againſt another <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick; <hi>Lutheran</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Lutheran;</hi> Reformed againſt Reformed; Anabaptiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Anabaptiſt, yea one Member of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire againſt another. <hi>The Gueſt is not ſafe with his Hoſt, nor the Father in Law with the Son in Law; the amity of Brethren alſo is rare,</hi> as the Poet
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpes ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite tutus. Nec ſocer a genere,</hi> &amp;c.</note> deſcribeth to the life the character of the former world, which the Deluge of waters, of old, waſht away. But if that the Lord Chriſt affirmeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>That a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> be of undoubted truth, how I pray ſhall the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſtians,</hi> in reſpect as well of the Religious Government, as of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42297:14"/>the ſecular, ſo many waies divided, be able to ſtand long.</p>
            <p>If, moreover the diſperſing of the holy people, ſhall have an end, as the Angel in <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh (<hi>chap.</hi> 12.) And if the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> ſhall again have mercy on them, and reſtore unto them their Kingdom (as the writings of the Prophets are full of promiſes concerning that matter) in what time, I pray, moſt likely doſt thou think, that will come to paſs? Will it not be, when they ſhall leaſt dare promiſe that thing to themſelves? Will they eſpecially then expect it, when they are broken with the ſenſe of their unworthineſs, whether haply the Lord, the God of their Fathers will vouchſafe of his meet Grace and Mercy, to remember them? Let whoſe will war againſt them, they will take Arms againſt no man. If any man ſmite them, they bear it. If any drive them from place to place, they give place, and fly away, as the chaſed Fawns of the Hind upon the mountaines. If any laies hands on them, and drags them to execution, to kill them, as ſwine, they deliver up themſelves to the ſlaughter. If any will kill them with the ſword, or burn them in the fire (as in <hi>Luſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> is often done) or attempt to bury them alive in pits (as not many years ſince was done in <hi>Polonia</hi>) they have nothing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they oppoſe, or defend themſelves, but prayers to God; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying him in his Judgments, and pleaſing themſelves after a ſort, in the puniſhment of their ſins; hoping in this, that the meaſure of their puniſhments, and chaſtiſements will at length be fulfilled, that God may again have mercy upon them. And whereas for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they were ſo averſe from the Chriſtians, that not in their greateſt neceſſity would they receive of us any ſupport or almes; now it is come to this paſs, that they not only gratefully accept of a morſel of bread, giving God thankes for it, but alſo come and deſire the ſame of us. Which indeed is no obſcure ſign on earth, that their converſion and redemption draweth nigh: Even as of old in <hi>Egypt,</hi> then was the time at hand, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> would make known himſelf to his Brethren, and receive all his Fathers Family into his protection, when it fell out, that his Brethren thinking no ſuch thing, came to receive from the hand of <hi>Joſeph</hi> (whom long ſince they had ſold, and delivered him into the hand of ſtrange Nations) bread, and ſuccours for the ſupport of life. And if now the Mercy for the <hi>Jewes</hi> is at hand, to wit, the Revelation of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42297:15"/>true <hi>Joſeph</hi> among them; it neceſſarily followes, that the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Babylon</hi> is at hand, and of neceſſity the deſtruction of the laſt Beſtial Monarchy (as afore we have often adviſed) is before the doores. For hear how <hi>Jeremiah</hi> (<hi>chap.</hi> 51.) knits theſe two together, namely, the <hi>Converſion of the Jewes,</hi> and the <hi>Subverſion of Babylon.</hi> For he ſaith, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Iſrael and Judah ſhall not alwaies be left of God, the Lord of Hoſts, in widdowhood, becauſe their Land was filled with tranſgreſſion, becauſe of the holy one of Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c. And immediately in <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>Fly ye out of the midſt of Babylon, and deliver every man his ſoul; be not cut off in her iniquity; for this is the time of Gods vengeance, he will render to her a recompenſe.</hi> Behold, ſo ſoon as God ſhall have mercy on his people, preſently he will gird himſelf to render vengeance on <hi>Babylon,</hi> for her injuſtice, Pride, and all Oppreſſion towards the miſerable diſperſed ſheep of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> As in the former Chap. the Lord complained, ſaying, <hi>The ſheeps (my people) are deſtroyed, their ſhepwards made them to go aſtray, they went from Mountain to Hill, forgetting the place of their lying down; all that found them devoured them, and their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſaid, we offend not, becauſe they have ſinned againſt the Lord, the habitation of Juſtice, even the Lord, the hope of their Fathers,</hi> Jer. 50.6, 7. Hear alſo how <hi>Joel</hi> joynes theſe two together (<hi>viz.</hi> the Converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Judgment of the Heathen which oppreſſed them, as mutual conſequents) <hi>chap.</hi> 3.1. where he ſaith, <hi>Behold in thoſe daies, and in that time, when I ſhall bring again the captivity of Judah and Jeruſalem, I will alſo gather all Nations, and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoſhaphat, and will plead with them there, for my people, and for my heritage Iſrael whom they have ſcattered among the Nations, and parted my Land, and they have caſt Lots for my people, and have given a Boy for a harlot, and ſold a Girle for wine, that they might drink.</hi> Note here how ſwiftly the one ſhall follow the other. Even ſo ſoon as the Cup of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is removed from <hi>Sion,</hi> ſo ſoon ſhall it be drunk to the Daughter of <hi>Edom. The puniſhment of thine iniquity is accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, O Daughter of Zion. He will no more carry thee away into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity: he will viſit thine iniquity, O Daughter of Edom. He will diſcover thy ſins,</hi> Lam. 4.22. As if the Lord had ſaid, <q>Thou haſt ſeen how I have viſited and diſcovered the iniquity of my people; how I have led them captive among all Nations:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42297:15"/>that theſe being admoniſhed by their example, might be wiſer, and might more diligently obſerve my Commandments than they have done. But becauſe thou haſt done no better, but worſe than they; and in ſtead of the Mercy with which thou ſhouldeſt have been enclined towards my people; and the righteouſneſs with which thou oughteſt to have convinced them of unrighteouſneſs, thou haſt done altogether the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: thou haſt uſed no mercy towards my people; and by thy unrighteouſneſs haſt hardned them in their iniquity, and whilſt thou di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt theſe things, thou wouldeſt juſtifie thy ſelf; fixing thine eyes not upon thy ſelf, but upon them; thou ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not the Beam in thine own eye, but didſt the More that was in thy Neighbours eye; meditating in thine heart; <hi>This people ſuffereth condigne puniſhment for their facts, becauſe they rejected the Lord Jeſus, who was the hope of their Forefathers, and that in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging againſt them, we cannot ſin.</hi> Yea thou haſt perſwaded thy ſelf that in thy afflicting, crucifying and killing of my people, thou haſt done my work, and rendered my revenge, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.4. But I; aſſoon as the iniquity of my people ſhall be finiſhed, even as I have done to them, ſo will I do to thee. I will viſit thee, and diſcover thy abominations. And as thou haſt exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed no mercy towards my people, ſo no body ſhall pity thee. As thou haſt done, ſo ſhall it be required to thee; in the Cup thou haſt drunk to others, ſhall it be drunk to thee. Yea the double thereof, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Time</hi> of the Converſion of the Jews, and the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Kingdom of Iſrael (of which all the Prophets are full) and by conſequence the end of the terrible 4th. Beaſt of <hi>Daniel, that it is at hand,</hi> that alſo may be ſufficiently demonſtrated by thoſe Signes which are preſcribed in the Old and New Teſtament; ſome at leaſt of which I will touch. And 1. out of 4
<note n="*" place="margin">otherwiſe the 2 of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dram</hi> 5.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> of <hi>Eſdr,</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. V. 1. <hi>Nevertheleſs, as concerning the tokens, behold he daies ſhall come, that they which ſhall dwell on the earth, ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aken in a great number, and the way of truth ſhall be hidden, and the Land ſhall be barren of Faith,</hi> 2. <hi>But iniquity ſhall be encreaſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve that which thou now ſeeſt, or that thou haſt heard long ago.</hi> 3. <hi>And he Land that thou now ſeeſt to have root, ſhalt thou ſee waſted ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</hi> 4. <hi>But if the moſt High grant thee to live, thou ſhalt ſee after
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42297:16"/>the THIRD TRUMPET, that the Sun ſhall ſhine ſuddenly again in the night; and the Moon thrice in the day.</hi> 5. <hi>And Blond ſhall drop out of the wood, and the ſtone ſhall give his voyce, and the people ſhall be troubled.</hi> 6. <hi>And even he ſhall rule; whom they looked not for, that dwell upon the earth; and the fowles ſhall take their flight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way together.</hi> 7. <hi>And the Sodomitiſh Sea ſhall cast out fiſh, and make a noiſe in the night, which many have not known: but they ſhall all hear the voyce thereof.</hi> 8. <hi>There ſhall be a Confuſion alſo in many places, and the fire ſhall be oft ſent out
<note n="*" place="margin">Margin. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aked.</hi>
                  </note> again, and the wild Beaſts ſhall change their places, and Menſtruous women ſhall bring forth Monſters.</hi> 9. <hi>And ſalt waters ſhall be found in the ſweet, and all friends ſhall deſtroy one another; then ſhall wit hide it ſelf, and underſtanding withdraw it ſelf into his ſecret Chamber.</hi> 10. <hi>And ſhall be ſought of many, and yet not be found: then ſhall unrighteouſneſs, and incontinency be multiplied on earth.</hi> 11. <hi>One Land alſo ſhall ask another, and ſay, Is Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs that maketh a man righteous gone through thee? And it ſhall ſay, No.</hi> 12. <hi>At the ſame time men ſhall hope, but nothing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: they ſhall labour, but their waies ſhall not proſper.</hi> And theſe are partly general ſignes, and partly particular, which God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels ſhall come to paſs, afore he ſhall again gather together <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and render to the Inhabitants of the earth according to their waies. All which ſignes without doubt have been abundantly enough fulfilled. The Inhabitants of the earth have heaped up to themſelves much Revenue, great Treaſures of Silver and Gold; mean while <hi>no Faith, no Truth can be found</hi> among men. That Countrey in which <hi>Eſdras</hi> then lived, when this Viſion happened unto him, to wit, the Land of <hi>Babylon,</hi> from that time it <hi>became deſolate;</hi> in divers places now, upon a ſudden the <hi>light hath ſhone forth by night,</hi> as if it had been day, and by day ſuch clow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings of the <hi>Light of the Sun hath ſuddenly riſen,</hi> that the <hi>Moon hath thrice in the day preſented it ſelf</hi> conſpicuous, and with its brightneſs, hath ſupplied the defect of the Sun. In divers places now, a few Weekes ſince in <hi>Poland, Bloud was ſeen to drop from wood, and to rain from Heaven.</hi> Yea alſo a <hi>Stone ſeemed to utter a voyce,</hi> as often as certain voices, divinely articulated to ſtrike a terrour into men were heard, as proceeding out of the ſtones of a Wall; the credit of which thing is aſſerted among Hiſtorians. As for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and Inſurrections of peoples, whereby <hi>new Lord-Rulers</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42297:16"/>have come unexpected, upon the Inhabitants of the Earth; how frequently hath that happened, and to this day happeneth? Who ſhall declare how often the <hi>Fowles of Heaven have tranſported them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to other haunts,</hi> becauſe of warlike commotions? That which is ſaid of the <hi>Sodomitiſh Sea,</hi> without doubt hath long ſince been fulfilled. Eſpecially this our moſt fruitful Age is moſt frequently famed for <hi>horrid Earthquakes, ſudden Conflagrations</hi> (as afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) <hi>the flight of wild Beaſts from place to place, abortive Births,</hi> both corporal, and ſpiritual, and horrid Monſters. As for Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Friends, how often canſt thou find <hi>ſweet waters in Salt? Friends contending againſt Friends, poſt-poning the League of amity, behind the preſent Intereſt.</hi> Which being ſo, the Prophet juſtly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyneth that <hi>then, Wit ſhall hide it ſelf, and underſtanding withdraw it ſelf into its ſecret Chamber; and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be ſought of many, and yet not be found: then ſhall unrighteouſneſs and incontinency be multiplied on earth. And that he that will ſeek righteouſneſs, though he run from Land to Land, from the River to the Sea, from one quarter of Heaven to the other, yet ſhall he find none.</hi> For where now can be found the true knowledge of God, and the genuine underſtanding of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cred Scriptures? How many have ſought it with all their ſtrength, and yet have not found it? When ever was ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity more abounding? ſo that it poſſeſſeth and fils all Courts, Temples, and Cloyſters: So that as concerning the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which juſtifies, <hi>i. e.</hi> truly renders men juſt before God, there is no more of it perceived at this day, than as if it had never been in the world. Finally, when ever was ſeen on earth more vain hope in men, and fruſtraneous labour? Behold then, ſeeing all theſe ſignes are fulfilled, what elſe may be inferred, but that the receiving and reſtauration of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the viſitation of the Inhabitants of the earth, conjoyned to it (whereby God will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to them according to their works) are at hand.</p>
            <p>If thou defireſt yet <hi>nearer ſignes,</hi> whereby thou maieſt be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted more fully concerning that precious time wherein the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God will begin to draw near, to viſit the Inhabitants of the earth, and put an end to the diſperſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of <hi>Sion,</hi> ſee in the ſame Book, <hi>chap.</hi> 6. Where thou wilt find the God of <hi>Eſdras</hi> thus ſpeaking, <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>And when the world that ſhall begin to vaniſh away ſhall be finiſhed (or ſealed) then will I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42297:17"/>ſhew theſe takens: The books ſhall be opened before the Firmament, and they ſhall ſee altogether.</hi> 21. <hi>And the children of an year old ſhall ſpeak with their voyces, and the women with child ſhall bring forth un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imely children, of thret or four moneths old, and they ſhall live, and be raiſed up,</hi> 22. <hi>And ſuddenly ſhall the ſown places appear unſown, the full storehouſes ſhall ſuddenly be found empty.</hi> 23. <hi>And the TRUMPET ſhall give a ſound, which when every man heareth, they ſhall be ſuddenly afraid.</hi> 24. <hi>At that time friends ſhall fight one againſt another, like enemies; and the earth ſhall ſtand in fear with thoſe that dwell therein: the ſprings of the Fountaines ſhall ſtand ſtill, and in three houres they ſhall not run.</hi> 25. <hi>Whoſoever remaineth, from all theſe I have told thee, ſhall eſcape, and ſee my ſalvation, and the end of the world,</hi> Behold concerning theſe ſignes I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay they are all, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ready fulfilled: Albeit of ſome of them, I am confident their beginnings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e now conſpicuous: as 1. <hi>That of the Books opened before the face of all peoples under the Firmament, viz.</hi> in the Bookes of mans Conſcience, which hither to have been as it were locked up, and ſealed by Superſtitions and Traditions of men, and Worſhips impoſed with violent force, although by them notwithſtanding all men at length are to be judged: Theſe Books I ſay, are begun to be opened before the face of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that all men univerſally ſhall look into them, and read them, and upon their inſight and reading of them, they ſhall be aſtoniſhed and humbled. Even as that good King <hi>Joſias,</hi> when the Book of the Law, ſometime loſt, was found again, and read before him, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22. For the time cometh, wherein the work of the Law, as written by the hand of God, in the hearts of men, ſhall be clearly laid open, and that by that ſaving Grace, which now begins to ſhine forth to all men. As to the Second, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>children of a year old speaking,</hi> if that be underſtood of ſimple ſpeaking, we have often ſeen it in our Age: Even as (thirdly) <hi>That alſo, that ſown places are ſuddenly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: and full ſterehouſes are ſuddenly found empty.</hi> But as to that, that the women with child ſhall bring forth abortives, <hi>of</hi> 3 <hi>or</hi> 4 <hi>moneths old, which ſhall remain alive, and be educated;</hi> and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> TRUMPET ſhall ſound to be heard over the univerſal world, to the terrifying of all the Inhanitants of the earth; and that laſt earthquake whereby the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall for</hi> 3 <hi>hour as be ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed,</hi> hath come to paſs; this I cannot affirm. But theſe ſignes, I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42297:17"/>judge, ſhall be, as the laſt labour and travel of this preſent world, to produce, and bring forth that other world. And that theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and travels ſhall mutually follow ſwiftly one another. Wherefore unleſs we will be prevented and deſtroyed by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look'd for coming of the Lord,
<note place="margin">N.B.</note> it will not behoove us to defer our repentance and reconciliation, unto the laſt ſignes; but ought to lay to heart thoſe former ſignes (which have been ſhewed, <hi>Eſdr. ch.</hi> 5.) and that by ſo much the more diligently, in that ſome of thoſe laſt begin to appear.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ſome man will ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>That Book of Eſdras is Apechry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, and therefore deſerves no credit, Jerom himſelf rejecting it as fabulous.</hi> I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Of the or dit to be given to the 4th. Book of <hi>Eſdras.</hi>
               </note> The Reaſons which <hi>Jerome</hi> brings for the confirmation of his opinion are ſolidly confuted by M. <hi>Abraham Bartolus</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Eſdras his Eagle</hi> (as before that by <hi>Theodorus Bibliander,</hi> a <hi>Tigurin</hi> Divine) producing Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions out of <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> and other Authors, ſufficiently va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, deſervedly to gain credit to this Book. But ſuppoſe that this Book ought to be more ſuſpected; go to, let us ſee neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, what Signes the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and his Apoſtles lay before us, by which, concerning the end of this preſent world, and the coming of Chriſt, to ſet up his Kingdom on earth, ſure Prognoſticks may be had; which, if they will agree with the Propheſie of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> what hinders, but that this Propheſie may find belief? Let us therefore hear what anſwer our Saviour gave to his Diſciples, when coming to him, asked the ſignes of his coming, and of the end of the world: <hi>In thoſe daies</hi> (Mark 13.) <hi>or ſtraight after the trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lation of thoſe daies</hi> (Mat. 24.29.) <hi>there</hi> ſhall be ſignes in the Sun, and the Moon, and the Stars, (<hi>Luke</hi> 21.25.) Behold there the ſignes in Heaven. Now if thou doſt deſire to know what ſignes of the Coming of Chriſt, and the end of the world ſhall be on earth, behold the Lord preſently ſubjoyneth in that cited place of <hi>Luke
<note place="margin">chap 21. v. 25, 26, 27, 18.</note>, upon the earth diſtreſs of Nations, with perplexity, the Sea, and the waves roaring, ment hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things, which are coming on the earth; for the Powers of Heaven ſhall be ſhaken. And then ſhall they ſee the Son of man coming in a Cloud, with power and great Glory. And when theſe things begin to come to paſs, then look up, and lift up your heads, for your Redemption draweth nigh.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42297:18"/>here a Propheſie above all exception! and words of ſo certain and undoubted truth, that heaven and earth ſhall ſooner paſs away, than one title of them. But what other thing doth this Propheſie ſound forth, than what we heard but now, of the ſignes both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth out of <hi>Eſdras? viz.</hi> In heaven, in reſpect of the Sun, Moon and Stars; In earth, by reaſon of the terrible things, by which the minds of men ſhall be greatly diſtreſſed, and made dubious. And although the Propheſie of <hi>Eſdras</hi> may ſeem in ſome particulars, ſomewhat to differ from Chriſts predictions, yet evidently it appears, that on both ſides nothing elſe is intended, then the reſtitution of the Jews, and by conſequence that viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Gentiles, or that fiery Judgment on all peoples who have oppreſſed the Elect. Not that only the Jews are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted <hi>thoſe Elect,</hi> which from the four winds (from the four corners of the world) are to be recollected, and gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: No by no means. For under that word are comprehended all pious and ſincere Chriſtians, of what Nation, or rank ſoever; <hi>viz.</hi> who being no leſs then the Jews, as <hi>disperſed ſheep,</hi> under the oppreſſion of falſe Chriſtians, and other Nations, do lie troden underfoot, and are deſervedly to be annumerated to the truly converted Jews, and genuine Children of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But, that we take here the word <hi>Elect,</hi> as more ſpecially belonging to the Jews; the reaſon is this, Becauſe when our Lord Jeſus Chriſt uttered theſe words, he had only Jews ſtanding before him, to whom he foretold thoſe things which properly appertained to their Redemption, by which they might acknowledge that the Kingdom of God (which <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26, 27. was promiſed to him) was now at hand, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.31. Unto them therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>When all theſe things ſhall begin to come to paſs</hi> (to wit, theſe ſigns in heaven and earth) <hi>then look up, and lift up your heads and hearts.</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>when ye ſhall ſee all theſe things fulfilled:</hi> for that would be too late, then to prepare for Redemption, but <hi>when ye ſhall ſee theſe things begin,</hi> then lift up your ſelves, and elevate your ſelves, above all earthly things; for your redemption is near.</p>
            <p>Now Candid Reader do thou judge, whether by thoſe things which we have before minded, concerning all thoſe ſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and thoſe we ſee done in our Age in Heaven and Earth, and which we
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42297:18"/>ſtill expect according to the Lords Propheſie, it may not juſtly be concluded, That even now, the Redemption of the Jews, and conſequently the coming of Chriſt to his Kingdom (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.) and the judgement by fire upon the world of u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>godly (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.) draws nigh. Neve theleſs, for the greater confirmation of the thing, and that we may manifeſt, that thoſe things which we have minded, concerning the Reſtitution of the Jews, and the end of this laſt Monarchy of the world, are not meer dictates of the Stars, or a ſimple ſingle Prognoſtication formed by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conjunction, but the matters born upon ſtrong and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed foundations: Come on, let us hear alſo <hi>what the Apoſtles have delivered concerning this thing: and whether the ſignes which they have given, are now paſt, or no; and what thence may be concluded?</hi> And firſt let us ſee what <hi>Peter,</hi> handling of the laſt times, and that fiery judgement wherewith the world of the ungodly ſhall be burnt, hath left us in writing. <hi>In the laſt daies ſhall come ſcoffers, walking after their own luſts; and ſaying, where is the promiſe of his coming, for ſince the fathers fell aſteep, all things continue as they were fro mthe beginning of the Creation,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.3, 4. Note here a SIGN, That in the laſt daies, <hi>i. e.</hi> neer the end of theſe daies (when now the coming of Chriſt ſhall be at hand) ſhall diſcover it ſelf. To wit, that then <hi>ſcoffers ſhall come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> who walking after their own luſts, will know nothing of this coming of Chriſt. And enquire I pray diligently, and make experience what anſwer thou ſhalt bring back, when once, by walking over the ſtreets of the great City (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8.) thou ſhalt talk with men; or with the Doctors and Ductors, the Leaders of the people, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians, as others, concerning the appro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ching of the time, wherein Chriſt will return on earth, to deſtroy the wicked, and to ſet up his Kingdom of righteouſneſs: thou ſhalt heat whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their own mouth will not betray them, that they altogether ſpeak the ſelf ſame thing, which is here premoniſhed concerning the ſcoffers of the laſt daies: <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>All things ſo continue, as they were from the Creation. That which now happens, the ſame likewiſe hath formerly happened, and therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude hence any certainty, are toys and phantaſms of mans own imagination.</q> Which being ſo, that we are now fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe times, when among all peoples, eſpecially Chriſtians
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42297:19"/>(who in times paſt were very haſty in their hope of ſetting up the Kingdom of Chriſt) in all Churches, Cloyſters, and Houſes, all places are full of Scoffers, why do we any longer doubt, but that now thoſe daies are near, in which the Heavens ſhall paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a great noiſe, the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, to deſtroy the ungodly with all their works, that there may ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the room thereof a new Heaven, and a new Earth, in which may dwell righteouſneſs? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. Wherefore it ought not to ſeem a wonder to any man, that we ſo diligently attend to theſe Signes of his coming, and do ſo interpret them.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ſome body will ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Peter doth not here ſpeak of thoſe things which are aforementioned,</hi> viz. <hi>concerning the Converſion of the Jews, and the total deſtruction of the</hi> 4th. <hi>Monarchy, and the ſetting up of the Kingdom of Chriſt on earth; but of the time wherein the Heavens ſhall paſs away, and the Elements ſhall be diſſolved,</hi> i.e. <hi>of the end of the world.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> We anſwer; what <hi>Peter</hi> affirmes touching the Heavens, Earth, and Elements, are not properly to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood according to the Letter, as the collation of Scriptures doth ſhew. For Chriſt will not by his coming deſtroy the works of his Father, Heaven, and Earth; but the works of the ungodly, and whatſoever curſe for mans ſake came upon Heaven and Earth, all this he will burn up with fire, and utterly purge out: as a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Goldſmith, that labours to burn, not the Gold and Silver, but the Droſs and Dregs, which adhere to the Gold and Silver. But as for the ſubſtance it ſelf of heaven, &amp; earth, &amp; all that God hath created, all thoſe things ſhall not be burnt by the coming of Chriſt, but ſhall only be renewed and purged: that where before un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs took place, now righteouſneſs there dwelleth: And where before, the violent poſſeſſed the Kingdoms of the world, there now the meek ſhall inherit. Thoſe heavens which the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly feign to themſelves, (as their hope and expectation) ſhall periſh: and thoſe Elements, or Rudiments of divine worſhip (even as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="*" place="margin">that is, <hi>Rudiments.</hi>
               </note> is taken in this ſenſe) wherein ſome fooliſhly ſtick all their life time, ſhall be diſſolved and burnt: yea the works of all men ſhall be conſumed, that a new heaven and a new earth may come forth; wherein may be beheld by all men all things in the glory of their perfection (as a pure workmanſhip of God the honour whereof may redound to him himſelf) as the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42297:19"/>Kingdom and City of God, the houſe and habitation of God and men, and a certain manifeſtation of the Righteouſneſs, Majeſty, and Love of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if indeed all theſe things ought to be ſo, and if it be true that with <hi>Peter, according to the promiſe</hi> (ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.) <hi>we expect a now Heaven, and a new Earth, wherein dwels righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.13. it ought not to ſeem ſtrange to us, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that be done, a fiery Judgment preceds on earth, to which theſe Signes in Heaven and earth have relation. A judgment, I ſay, to deliver both <hi>Jews</hi> and Chriſtians hitherto oppreſſed; and to deſtroy all the deſtroyers; and to reſtore all things on earth; and to deſtroy them that have deſtroyed the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. Behold now we ſee what ſignes the Ap. <hi>Peter</hi> hath ſet touching the coming of the Lord; and how they have been fulfilled long ſince in an high degree: ſo that in regard thereof nothing now remaines to be expected, but the thing it ſelf, ſignified by thoſe ſignes.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee moreover, what the Ap. <hi>Paul,</hi> that choſen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel diſcourſeth concerning the laſt times; and how he limbs out in lively colours the men that ſhall live in that time. <hi>They ſhall be</hi> (ſaith he, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.) <hi>Lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthank ful, unholy, without na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ural affection, truce breakers, falſe accuſers, inconti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, fierce, desp ſers of them that are good, traitors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures, more then lovers of God. Having a form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but denying the power thereof.</hi> What ſeemeth to thee Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? Are our times deſcribed, or is it longer yet to be expected till this kind of men come upon the Stage? If thou wilt acknowledge that we are indeed devolved upon or into thoſe times, wherein every where men are found to be <hi>Lovers of their own ſelves, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, Boaſters, Proud,</hi> &amp;c. And that they alſo who carry a form of Godlineſs, and would be reputed for godly, do poſſeſs more of its external form, than of the internal truth of it, denying the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power of Godlineſs, which conſiſteth in ſpirit and truth; what wonder if we accompt the aforeſaid ſignes in Heaven for fore Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and fore-runners, of the conſummation of thoſe daies wherein the madneſs of all thoſe men, ſhall be made manifeſt to all men, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. that ſome when 'at length true right couſneſs, love of God, and the ſincere power of Godlineſs, may come in their room.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42297:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42297:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42297:21"/>
            <p>But that it may more clearly appear, that thoſe things which we have mentioned concerning the reſtitution of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the end of the laſt Monarchy, and have by this Conjunction of the Princely or chief Stars inferred that they are at the door, are not meer Aſtrological Prognoſticks, but matters founded in the Word of God: Let us go alſo to the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> that beloved Apoſtle, who was wont to lie in Chriſts boſom, and ſee what he ſaith of this matter in the Book of the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, which Chriſt himſelf by his Angel dictated to him, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to write it to the Churches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is there read, that the time ſhall come, wherein the <hi>Saints of God ſhall be made Kings and Prieſts to God,</hi> that as Kings they may reign on earth, ch. 1. v. 6. &amp; ch. 5. v. 10. which thing becauſe it cannot be done without the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor before the Kingdom of the Beaſt and of the falſe Prophet be overthrown, it neceſſarily followes, that if ever that time ought to come to paſs, wherein the Saints ſhall reign on earth, thoſe former things ought firſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, or go before; and if they now precede, and we are come to theſe laſt times, the conſequence is neceſſary, that thing to be at the door.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. of this Book (of <hi>Revel.</hi> which is as a kind of, <hi>Compendium</hi> of the whole Hiſtory of the Church, or Temple of God, beginning from the treading of it underfoot on earth, and ending in the opening of it in heaven) we read that <hi>the treading of the holy City underfoot, the propheſying of the two Witneſſes in Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath and Aſhes, and the lying of their dead Bodies in the ſtreets of the great City, are limited to certain periods of Moneths, Daies, and Times.</hi> Which being run out, the end of the world will not as yet follow, but only the reſtauration of the holy City trampled, the raiſing of the two Witneſſes to life, and that in the ſight of their enemies. And after theſe things will follow at length, that <hi>great Earthquake, whereby the tenth part of the City ſhall fall,</hi> and 7 Companies of men ſhall be ſlain, as alſo the <hi>third we,</hi> and the <hi>laſt Trumpet.</hi> Sufficiently clear therefore it appeareth to us who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready have ſeen, and do ſee the holy City of the Church trampled, and the bodies of the Witneſſes lie in the ſtreets of the ſaid City, voyd of life, that nothing neceſſarily is more nearly to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than that the fulneſs of the Gentiles come in, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:42297:21"/>(witneſs the Ap. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.) be ſaved, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from her trampling (<hi>Luke</hi> 21.24.) and ſhake off her duſt, and be cloathed with her Glory (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.2.) but that great City ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually called <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> utterly to fall. And ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe now all the moſt excellent Chronologers, and Searchers of times, and who ever beſtowed their labour on the computation of theſe 42 <hi>Moneths,</hi> the 1260 <hi>daies,</hi> or of the <hi>time and times and half a time,</hi> are become like a woman great with child; which having paſſed the time of her reckoning, doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily expect every hour, the paines and labours of travel. And ſeeing that the mean while thoſe ſignes in Heaven and Earth break forth, and offer themſelves to open view, who cannot conceive that the next change to follow as the expected birth, of which all the Prophets and Apoſtles have propheſied, is now before the door; and we are now duly warned, that we make our ſelves ready.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We read in the 16th. Chap. of <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of the 7 Vials.</note> of the 7 <hi>Vials of the wrath of God,</hi> to be poured out upon the earth, <hi>before any man can enter into the Temple of the divine Glory,</hi> ch. 15.8. Surely 5 of theſe Vials now, long ſince have been poured out. The 1. by and by after the times of the Apoſtles, producing that evil, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Uſcer of falſe Brethren, and rapacious Wolves, who by degrees brake forth, and brought upon the Church many troubles and griefs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2. The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>Vial</hi> was in the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, about 300 years after the Birth of Chriſt, when the body of the Church, which formerly had been a ſeparated thing from the world, (as earth from Sea) is now again mixt with the people of the world; as the earth which is again ſwallowed up of the Sea. For then this Sea, by the pouring out of the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Vial, is made as the bloud of a dead man, and every ſoul, which lived in that Sea, died by that plague, <hi>ch.</hi> 16.3. The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Vial</hi> was poured out about the 600 year after Chriſts Birth, in the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3. who was by the Emperour <hi>Phocas</hi> declared <hi>Head of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church.</hi> For then the Rivers, and Fountains of waters were turned into bloud, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe ſpiritual Orders of <hi>Eremites, Moncks,</hi> and the like, who from the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, had kept themſelves ſeparated from the Sea of the peoples, they alſo now began to be conformed to this Head of the Church, and to be made partakers of this predominion, which the Pope arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42297:22"/>to himſelf, and of all violence upon the conſciences of men. Becauſe therefore they alſo powred out the Bloud of the Saints and Prophets, therefore the moſt righteous God gave them bloud to drink; bloud, I ſay, in compariſon, that whereas they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore refreſhed with living waters, now they drink meer bloud, as of a dead man in whom there was no life or power. The 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Vial</hi> was poured out, about the year after Chriſts birth, 1100 or 1200, and continued to the time of Reformation, when the wrath of God was poured out upon the <hi>Sun, i.e.</hi> the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> that only light, which had remained after the loſs of thoſe aforeſaid Saints. And deſervedly is the light of the Scripture compared to the Sun; becauſe as the Sun is ſet in the Firmament, that it may ciſtinguiſh between day and night, times of daies and years; ſo the S. Scripture (conſiſting of a ſure word of Propheſie) is given to that end, that it may teach us prudently to diſcern between light and darkneſs, between the various diſpenſations of God. Moreover, that which <hi>Syrach,</hi> chap. 42.16. ſpeaks concerning the Sun, <hi>that it doth illuſtrate all things, and the work thereof is full of the Glory of God;</hi> the ſame may we affirm concerning the S. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it is a light that illuſtrates all things, and is a work full of the glory of God. For never any eminent thing happened, nor doth yet happen, or ever ſhall come to paſs, but that (S. Script.) foreſaw it, and foretold it, ſo as if any man would have eyes deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to view his work, without all doubt he might ſee it full of the glory of God. Moreover, as there is in the Sun heat, beſides light, from which none can hide himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. which heat warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, refreſheth, and enliveneth this man, but torments, burnes, and kils another man: So in the S. Script. beſides that light of diſcerning, there is heat, or a certain vital power, from which no man can hide himſelf; and by which ſome men are comforted, refreſhed, and quickned; others are tormented, burned, and ſlain. And when this is done (<hi>viz.</hi> that men are not warmed and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the uſe of the S. Scripture, but are burnt and incenſed) that thing no otherwiſe comes to paſs, then from their evil diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the pouring out of this Vial of the wrath of God upon them, whereby men by occaſion of the Scriptures, wax hot one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, and with an inordinate zeal, as with fire, devour one another, as the Hiſtories of thoſe times do abundantly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42297:22"/>The 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Vial</hi> may be ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be poured out about the year 1520, when the <hi>Rom.</hi> Empire, to wit, the Throne of the Beaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan ſignally to be obſcured, from whence there came much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the Favourers and Adorers of the Beaſt, ſo as they bit their tongues for grief; and which is more, by meanes of their grief and malignant ulcers, they blaſphemed God. The obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this Kingdom conſiſted 1. In that about that time, very many Cities, and Provinces, yea Kingdomes revolted from the yoke of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion. Nor was this only ſo, but (2.) This obſcuring conſiſted alſo in many tumults of war, which were raiſed by this change of Religion. Which obſcuring of that Kingdom at laſt, came to that, that now in the year 1619, by meanes of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> war, the Axe began to be laid to the very root of that beſtial Throne: which (Throne) although it continue to this day, yet is not the darkning paſt, but out of all doubt will be aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, until that day wherein the Beaſt ſhall be taken and caſt into the Like of Fire and Brimſtone. Foraſmuch therefore as <hi>theſe</hi> 5 <hi>Vials</hi> are already poured out, and the obſcuring of the Beaſts Throne, is dayly more and more encreaſed, what I pray comes next to be expected by us, but that the <hi>ſixth Vial,</hi> which is now pouring out, ſhall make way for thoſe Kings that ſhall come from the Eaſt, of whom <hi>Baruch</hi> makes mention, <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 5. &amp;c. that the Stone, out out of the Mountain without hands (of which <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.45.) may caſt down, break in pieces, and deſtroy all the Kingdomes of the earth, and in ſtead of them, that ſtone may fill the whole earth? And if this be that thing which comes next to be expected by us, what marvel if we refer theſe ſignes in Heaven and Earth now concurring, to this Matter? and that we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as foretellers of the <hi>Jews</hi> Converſion, and the ſubverſion of the laſt Monarchy of the world?</p>
            <p n="4">4. We read alſo in <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. <hi>That a time will one day come, when the</hi> 10 <hi>Horns of the Beaſt, on which the Harlet ſits</hi> (which 10 Horns are 10 Kings, who have long adored the Beaſt, and have committed fornication with the whore) <hi>ſhall in that agree together, hat with hatred they perſecute the where, and make her deſolate and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ked,</hi> chap. 17.16. And we know who is that Harlot, and who are thoſe Kings which have ſo long ſerved her; <hi>viz.</hi> the Kings of <hi>France, Spain, Poland, Hungary, Behemiah, England, Scotland,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42297:23"/>Portugal, Suedland</hi> and <hi>Denmark:</hi> All which, together with the Pope (lifting up himſelf as the Head of the Catholick Church) nad their riſe. And becauſe we ſee that in many of theſe Kings there hath been long ſince a mind, that if they could, would long ago have devoured her fleſh: but concerning the reſt of the Kings, which hitherto have adhered to the Harlot, 'tis evident, that they alſo are gone into parties, and diſſent from her, and begin to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare war againſt her: who thence may not conclude the death of that Whore,
<note place="margin">Gerariae.</note> and by conſequence, the deſtruction of that <hi>Gerarian</hi> ſeven-headed-Beaſt, to be before the doores. And albeit there were no ſignes of this extant in Heaven, yet to quick-ſighted men, and they who believe the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, thoſe ſignes of it on earth, which we ſee with our eyes, and touch with our hands,
<note place="margin">N.B.</note> may be ſufficient.</p>
            <p>Behold now I have demonſtrated that, that ſame faithful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of the aforeſaid Book, Printed at <hi>Groning,</hi> and written upon occaſion of the inſtant Conjunction of all the Planets in the fiery Sign of (♐) <hi>Sagitary,</hi> is moſt worthy to be heedfully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and to be laid up in the inmoſt Cloſets of our hearts; ſeeing the matters there ſet forth, are not vain Phantaſmes of mans Brain,
<note place="margin">☞</note> of idle figments of ſuperſtitious Aſtrology, but a ſure cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain truth, founded in Nature, and on the Scriptures; agreeing not only with the Tradition and Experience of the Ancients, but alſo with the Predictions of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and of his beloved Apoſtles, <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> and <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I will conclude with the words of our Lord, full of Conſolation and Love, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.8, &amp;c. And when theſe things begin to come to paſs, then look up, and lift up your heads, for your Redemption draweth nigh. 29. <hi>And he spake to them a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, behold the Fig-tree, and all the Trees,</hi> 30. <hi>When they now ſhoot forth, ye ſee and know of your own ſelves, that Summer is now nigh at hand. V.</hi> 31. <hi>So likewiſe ye when ye ſee theſe things come to paſs, know ye that the Kingdom of God is at hand.</hi> Go to, let us lay aſide whatſoever might hinder us. Be we like to Servants, who with their Loynes girt, and their Lamps burning, expect their Maſter. Let us ſhake off the duſt of the Earth, and lift up our heads with our hearts heaven-ward; clearing our ſelves from all Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, before it be too late; that is, before thoſe laſt ſignes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42297:23"/>which ſhall unexpectedly ſlay the world. For thoſe things which Chriſt foretold, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. ſhall come to paſs, are more than begun to be fulfilled. And unleſs we make haſt, thoſe, laſt Signes which ſhall immediately accompany Chriſts coming, will be now preſent, and come upon us unaware. Now the Figuree hath begen to put forth her leaves, now her branch begins to wax tender. Yet truly thoſe natural Branchek of that ſame <hi>Noble Olive-tree</hi> (of which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to be tender, (as I before noted, for I ſpeak not of a thing un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rienced (acknowledging themſelves to be great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, giving Glory to God, and juſtifying him in all his Judgments exerciſed upon them; and ſubmitting themſelves without any reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to all afflictions, reproaches, and puniſhments, and anxiouſly expecting if at any time God will remember them, and have mercy upon them. Moreover, do not thoſe ſignes of the end of this world, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Beaſts laſt violence, and of Government every where over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing it ſelf, begin to bud forth? Therefore whoſoever will not be up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are deſtroyed, and periſh with the world, it is of neceſſity that he haſten. For moſt certainly the Summer is at hand, <hi>i.e.</hi> that glorious Kingdom of God (of which all the Prophets have propheſied, of which alſo Chriſt ſo often moniſhed his Diſciples, and they us; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting us continually with that Conſolation) is now at the door. O bleſſed Summer, and with all Prayer to be deſired; in which all thoſe excellent fruits ſhall be preſented to the eyes of all, in Production whereof God and Chriſt have laboured ſo many thouſand years! whereby at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt bountiful God may be truly acknowledged, prayſed, and ſanctified, among all peoples, and inhabitants of the whole world, for the works of his hands, and for the unſpeakable riches of his Grace, Truth, and Love, and Faithfulneſs towards Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. O bleſſed Kingdom, where God alone ſhall be Kingi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> vvhich to him only, vvho hath redeemed us vvith his precious bloud from among all peoples, all povver and vviſdom, and honour, and ſtrength, and riches ſhall be given vvith one conſent, of all Creatures, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angels or men.</p>
            <p>The God and Father of our Lord JESUS CHRIST, who by the Goſpel of his Son hath called us unto that Kingdom, open in us our underſtanding to lay theſe things to heart, that conforming our ſelves wholly to theſe things, we may be meet to have our part in the delicacies of this Summer, and the ineffable Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Kingdom of our Lord JESU CHRIST, Bleſſed for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde to the Book the Propheſie of <hi>Tobit,</hi> chap. 14. v. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:42297:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Pourtraiture</hi> how the Planets ſtood above one another (every one according to his Altitude) yet all of them under the ſame Sign <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> Decemb. 1/12.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of planetary postions</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 40. lin. 9, 10. at the words <hi>[the deſtruction of that Gerarian ſeven-headed Beaſt]</hi> read (if ye pleaſe) thus, <hi>[the deſtruction of that Carriereſs, Portereſs, or drudge-bearer of the ſeven-headed Beaſt.]</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42297:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
